<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The eunuch. A tragedy: as it hath been acted with great applause. / Written by William Hemmings, Oxon..</title>
            <author>Hemings, William, b. 1602?</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1687</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 148 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 30 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A43305</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H1421</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R17570</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12256293</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12256293</idno>
            <idno type="VID">57541</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A43305)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 57541)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2247:6, 868:15)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The eunuch. A tragedy: as it hath been acted with great applause. / Written by William Hemmings, Oxon..</title>
                  <author>Hemings, William, b. 1602?</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 54, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by J.B. and are to be sold by Randal Taylor near Stationers-Hall,,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1687..</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"Licensed, March 26. 1687. Roger L'Estrange."</note>
                  <note>The copy of this item at reel 868:15 is incorrectly identified as Wing H1521.</note>
                  <note>Reproductions of originals in Huntington Library (reel 868:15), and Newberry Library (reel 2247:6).</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:57541:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE EUNUCH. A TRAGEDY: As it hath been Acted with Great Applauſe.</p>
            <p>Written By <hi>William Hemmings,</hi> Oxon.</p>
            <p>Licenſed, <hi>March</hi> 26. 1687. <hi>Roger</hi> L'<hi>Estrange.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>J. B.</hi> and are to be ſold by <hi>Randal Taylor</hi> near <hi>Stationers-Hall,</hi> 1687.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dramatis_personae">
            <pb facs="tcp:57541:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:57541:2"/>
            <head>Dramatis Perſonae.</head>
            <list>
               <item>The <hi>Eunuch.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Old King.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Clotaire,</hi> The Young King.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Clovis,</hi> His Brother.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Fredegonde,</hi> The Queen.</item>
               <item>Old <hi>Briſac.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Charles Briſac,</hi> His Son.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Aphelia,</hi> His Daughter.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Landrey,</hi> The Queens Favourite.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Dumaine,</hi> Brother to the <hi>Eunuch.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Lamot,</hi> His Friend.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Burbon,</hi> Officers and Soldiers.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Lanoue,</hi> Officers and Soldiers.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Martile,</hi> Officers and Soldiers.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Iſabel,</hi> Ladies Attending the Queen.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Julia,</hi> Ladies Attending the Queen.</item>
               <item>Page.</item>
               <item>Lackey.</item>
               <item>Two Watchmen.</item>
               <item>A Meſſenger.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="play">
            <pb facs="tcp:57541:3"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:57541:3"/>
            <div n="1" type="act">
               <head>ACT <hi>I.</hi>
               </head>
               <div n="1" type="scene">
                  <head>SCENE <hi>I.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Dumaine <hi>and</hi> Lamot, <hi>like two Poor Souldiers.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Dumaine.</speaker>
                     <l>WE are not ſafe <hi>Lamot,</hi> this Bawdy Peace</l>
                     <l>Begets a War within me, our Swords worn</l>
                     <l>For Ornament not uſe, the Drum, and Trumpet</l>
                     <l>Sing Drunken Carrols, and the Cannon ſpeaks</l>
                     <l>Health, not Confuſion; Helmets turned to Cups;</l>
                     <l>Our bruiſed Arms adminiſter diſcourſe</l>
                     <l>For Tables, and for Tav<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>rns, where the Souldier</l>
                     <l>Oft finds a pity, not relief: Pl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> tell thee</l>
                     <l>We are walking Images, the ſign of men,</l>
                     <l>And bear about us nothing but the form</l>
                     <l>Of man, that's manly.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lamot.</speaker>
                     <p>We are c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>le indeed.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Dum.</speaker>
                     <l>Yes my <hi>Lamot,</hi> and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>he ungratefull Time</l>
                     <l>As coldly doth reward ut, all our Actions,</l>
                     <l>Attempts of Valour look'd into with Eyes</l>
                     <l>Philmed with Contempt, when ye Gods, ye know,</l>
                     <l>It is our Gifts they ſee yet: Oh I am Mad!</l>
                     <l>The very Bread that lends them Life to ſcorn us,</l>
                     <l>Our Bloods have paid for, yet demand a bit,</l>
                     <l>Or ask of this Old-Sattin-Belly'd-Sir,</l>
                     <l>Or Madam-Toothleſs, with her Velvet Sconce,</l>
                     <l>And you ſhall hear their rotten Lungs pronounce</l>
                     <l>The Whip, and Whipſtock.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lamot.</speaker>
                     <p>Patience, Great <hi>Dumaine.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Dum. Lamot,</speaker>
                     <l>Thou know'ſt, I dare be Patient.</l>
                     <l>With what an equal Temper did I breath,</l>
                     <l>Under the Frozen Climate of the North,</l>
                     <l>Where in mine Arms, the Sheets of War, I Slept;</l>
                     <l>My Bed being feathered with the down of Heaven,</l>
                     <l>I have lain down a Man, and riſe a Snow-Ball;</l>
                     <l>Yet theſe have been my Paſtimes, which I have born</l>
                     <l>as willingly, as I receiv'd them Nobly.</l>
                     <l>The Queens black Envy which doth ſtill remain,</l>
                     <l>And peeps through every Limb ſhe bears about her,</l>
                     <l>Fated to ruine us, does not ſwell my Gall;</l>
                     <pb n="2" facs="tcp:57541:4"/>
                     <l> No, nor this willing Beggery I wear</l>
                     <l>To cloud me from her Malice; by the Gods,</l>
                     <l>This Baſtard-getting-Peace unſpirits me,</l>
                     <l>A greater corraſive to my Active Soul,</l>
                     <l>Then all paſt-ills whatever.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lamot.</speaker>
                     <l>Cool your Rage,</l>
                     <l>And be as Wiſe as Valiant, this is not time</l>
                     <l>To vent your Paſſions like a Woman;</l>
                     <l>A Souldiers Tongue moves only in his Sword.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Dum.</speaker>
                     <l>You are an expert Tutor and I thank you;</l>
                     <l>Our Wrongs would add a Spirit to the Dead,</l>
                     <l>And make them fight our quarrels. Who comes here?</l>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>A Floriſh, Enter</hi> Landrey, 2 <hi>or</hi> 3 <hi>Lords,</hi> 2 <hi>or</hi> 3 <hi>Petitioners, who by his followers are ſlighted off; they as grived re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn back again, whilſt he paſſes on in State.</hi>
                     </stage>
                     <l>The Minion to our Queen! Oh what a train</l>
                     <l>The Painted Peacock bears! Death! were I <hi>Jove</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>But only for this Gyant.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lamot.</speaker>
                     <p>Still intemperate.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Dum.</speaker>
                     <l>Theſe are the fruits of Peace, upſtarts, &amp; ſlatteries;</l>
                     <l>Tell me <hi>Lamot,</hi> can this ſame Marchant-Man,</l>
                     <l>Think or Commit a Sin, tho' never ſo Horrid</l>
                     <l>But it is candid o're, and from his Vice,</l>
                     <l>Exceſſive praiſe, and plaudites ariſe.</l>
                     <l>Were I the King! but he is willfull Blind;</l>
                     <l>And by the Horns ſhe rocks him faſt aſleep,</l>
                     <l>Before the Wanton and hot-Blooded Queen</l>
                     <l>Should have the Licenſe, but to be ſuſpected</l>
                     <l>With ſuch a Knight of Gingerbred as this is,</l>
                     <l>A Guilded Fleſh-fly; I would lock Her up,</l>
                     <l>Yea chain the Evil Angel in a Box,</l>
                     <l>And Houſe her like a Silk-Worm.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lamot.</speaker>
                     <l>Pardon Sir,</l>
                     <l>The good Old King's unable.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Dum.</speaker>
                     <l>Worſe and Worſe,</l>
                     <l>And therefore muſt admit an upſtart-Page,</l>
                     <l>Now raiſed to Honour by his Lawleſs Luſt:</l>
                     <l>Mayor of the Palace, and the Duke of <hi>France;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>The next ſtep is the Crown; Oh Peaſant State,</l>
                     <l>When Owls are aired in the Cedars top,</l>
                     <l>And Daws compare with Eagles.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lamot.</speaker>
                     <l>Like to like.</l>
                     <l>What was our <hi>Fredegonde</hi> but <hi>Golſanda's</hi> Maid?</l>
                     <l>A Princeſs, (Oh my Soul!) ſo Heaven'd above her,</l>
                     <l>That <hi>Fredegonde</hi> appears a Hell of darkneſs;</l>
                     <l>Yet does our Childrick, our old doting King,</l>
                     <l>Set up a Diſhclout againſt a Diadem.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <pb n="3" facs="tcp:57541:4"/>
                     <speaker>Dum.</speaker>
                     <p>'Twere good the King would Execute them both.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lamot.</speaker>
                     <l>Execute them! For his beſt Blood he dares not;</l>
                     <l>The no-Chaſt-Queen is great in Faction,</l>
                     <l>Followed and Sainted by the Multitude,</l>
                     <l>Whoſe judgments ſhe has linked unto her purſe,</l>
                     <l>And rather bought a Love then found it:</l>
                     <l>She has a working Spirit, an active Brain,</l>
                     <l>Apt to conceive, and wary in her wills;</l>
                     <l>Beſides, her Sons. (the Pillars of State)</l>
                     <l>Supports her like an Atlas, where the ſits;</l>
                     <l>And like the Heavens commands our faces beneath her.</l>
                     <l>She is the greater Light, the King a Star,</l>
                     <l>Which only glares but through her influence.</l>
                     <stage>A Floriſh.</stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Dum</speaker>
                     <l>Heark the Thunder of the War; now! out of Tune,</l>
                     <l>This Peace corrupting all things makes them ſpeak.</l>
                     <l>What means this moſt Adulterate noiſe?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lamot.</speaker>
                     <l>Receiv't.</l>
                     <l>This is a Night of Jubile, and the King</l>
                     <l>Solemnly Feaſts for his Wars happy ſucceſs:</l>
                     <l>Beſides his Sons and he are knit again;</l>
                     <l>We ſhall have Maſques and Revellings to Night.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Dum.</speaker>
                     <l>Now the Great Gods confound this pick-thank noiſe;</l>
                     <l>The Drum and Trumpets are turn'd flatteries,</l>
                     <l>And <hi>Mars</hi> himſelf a Bawd to grace their Ryots.</l>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>Enter the</hi> Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuch <hi>with two fair Suits, Hats, Feathers, Rapiers, and all things an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwerable, flings them a Letter, and to each a purſe of Gold; and after a little pauſe departs.</hi>
                     </stage>
                     <l>What Viſion's this? 'Tis Gold both right &amp; fair;</l>
                     <l>Sure I dream not.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lamot.</speaker>
                     <l>I cannot tell, but he</l>
                     <l>That takes this from me ſhall full ſoon perceive</l>
                     <l>I do not ſleep nor ſlumber: 'Twas the <hi>Eunuch.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Dum.</speaker>
                     <p>That needs no deciding.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lamot.</speaker>
                     <l>What Papers that?</l>
                     <l>If it be Chorus unto this dumb ſhew,</l>
                     <l>Read it <hi>Dumaine.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Dum.</speaker>
                     <l>Daſterd Hand, why ſhak'ſt thou?</l>
                     <stage>Takes up the Letter &amp; ſeems to tremble.</stage>
                     <l>The Queen!</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lamot.</speaker>
                     <l>Blaſted <hi>Dumaine!</hi> Give me the Scrowl;</l>
                     <l>Were ſhe a Fury, nay the Queen of Hell,</l>
                     <l>Tho' every word did Thunder I would read it.</l>
                     <stage>He Reads.</stage>
                     <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                        <body>
                           <p>
                              <hi>As ye are Souldiers truly Valiant, we Honour ye; as poor, we pity ye, and have ſent ye that which will render ye as compleat Courtiers, as un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daunted Souldiers:</hi> Damaine, Lamot, <hi>let is ſuffice we know ye, for our Eye is Every where, whilſt we remember your Works, we ſhall ſtudy to forget your Parents Injuries: Fear nothing, for your hitherto concealment
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:57541:5"/>we will get your Pardons, and whilſt we breath, breath your kind Miſtriſs; if you dare truſt us, and build upon our Fortunes, appear at Court to Night ſo adorned as ſhall become your Honours and our Friends.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <closer>
                              <signed>Fredegonde.</signed>
                           </closer>
                        </body>
                     </floatingText>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Dum.</speaker>
                     <p>How do you relliſh this? What now <hi>Lamot?</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lamot.</speaker>
                     <l>We'le take the Gracious proſſer of the Queen,</l>
                     <l>She's Princely vow'd our Friend; beſides what Ill</l>
                     <l>Can we expect from her, who might have ſent</l>
                     <l>Her Murdering Miniſter, and Slain us here</l>
                     <l>Had ſhe intended foul-play; ſhe is Noble.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Dum.</speaker>
                     <p>But—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lamot</speaker>
                     <p>What but?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Dum.</speaker>
                     <p>Her Murder'd Brothers memory;</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lamot.</speaker>
                     <l>When he fell, we were too young for Traytors,</l>
                     <l>Tho' not for Torments, had we been apprehended:</l>
                     <l>For in the high diſpleaſure of this Queen</l>
                     <l>All our Poſterity was doom'd: Some felt the Wheel,</l>
                     <l>Some Racked, ſome Hanged, others Impaled on ſtakes,</l>
                     <l>And had not we been then in <hi>Wittenburgh,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>And paſt the fury of the Tyrants reach,</l>
                     <l>We'd added to the Number of the Dead.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Dum.</speaker>
                     <p>And think you ſtill we ſhall not?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lamot</speaker>
                     <l>By my Life,</l>
                     <l>It's Murder to ſuſpect her, we'le to Court,</l>
                     <l>Our Lives are all that we can looſe, our fame</l>
                     <l>No Art can Murder, nor time raſe our name.</l>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="scene">
                  <head>SCENE. <hi>II.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Fredegonde <hi>and the</hi> Eunuch.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Queen.</speaker>
                     <p>What coference did they maintain with thee?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Eunuch.</speaker>
                     <l>None farther then the Language of their Eyes;</l>
                     <l>They look'd on me as if they meant me thanks,</l>
                     <l>Which their Amazement rob'd me of.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Queen.</speaker>
                     <p>Know'ſt thou them?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Eunuch.</speaker>
                     <l>No, deareſt Lady, they appeared to me</l>
                     <l>Like to the Silent Poſtures in the Arras,</l>
                     <l>Only the form of Men with ſtrange Faces.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Queen.</speaker>
                     <l>Come take them then, they are our Enemies,</l>
                     <l>Whom I have Angled with that Golden Bait;</l>
                     <l>Their Parents waded in my Brothers Blood;</l>
                     <pb n="5" facs="tcp:57541:5"/>
                     <l> For which I'le be revenged of all their kin,</l>
                     <l>Did they increaſe as faſt as I could kill,</l>
                     <stage>Draws the Cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain and ſhews a Picture.</stage>
                     <l>I'de ever Kill, that they may ſtill increaſe.</l>
                     <l>This Picture drawn by an Italian,</l>
                     <l>(Which ſtill I keep to whet my Anger on)</l>
                     <l>Does repreſent the Murther of my Brother,</l>
                     <l>For Raviſhing this Beauteous peice of Ill;</l>
                     <stage>Points to the Pictures.</stage>
                     <l>A Cruel and a Terrible Miſtake,</l>
                     <l>To Murther <hi>Clodymer,</hi> for <hi>Clotair's</hi> fact.</l>
                     <l>For which behold how <hi>Fredegond's</hi> revenged:</l>
                     <stage>Points ſtill.</stage>
                     <l>This old <hi>Dumaine</hi> and Father to this Maid,</l>
                     <l>With all his Kindred, Sociates, and Allyes</l>
                     <l>(Theſe brace of wicked ones, and this raviſht Whore,</l>
                     <l>The fair and fatal cauſe of theſe events</l>
                     <l>Only excepted) are here; here in this Picture.</l>
                     <l>Here's one bereft of Hands, and this of Tongue,</l>
                     <l>Finger thy Lute <hi>Maria,</hi> Sing out <hi>Iſabel,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Heark Heark, <hi>Caſtrat,</hi> the Muſick of the Spheres,</l>
                     <l>O raviſhing touch! Heark how the others voice</l>
                     <l>Ecchoes the Lute, Is't not a Divine ſoftneſs, Ha, ha, ha!</l>
                     <l>I do expect they now ſhould rail extremely;</l>
                     <l>I prethee Scould at me good <hi>Iſabel,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>A little of the Woman; no! <hi>Maria,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Within the loathed Circle of mine Eyes</l>
                     <l>Anchor thy ſingers; Alas! thy Nails are pared;</l>
                     <l>Nor has poor <hi>Iſabel</hi> a Tongue to ſcould with:</l>
                     <l>Two hory Greybeards in this angle lyes,</l>
                     <l>Will find their way to Hell without their Eyes.</l>
                     <stage>Stabs the Picture.</stage>
                     <l>Villains that Kill'd my Brother, how does this relliſh thee,</l>
                     <l>To Execute Men in Pictures? Is't not rare?</l>
                     <l>Is't not a paſtime for the Gods to gaze on?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Eunuch.</speaker>
                     <l>Were but <hi>Crotilda</hi> here, and theſe two Youngſters,</l>
                     <l>It were a paſtime for the Gods to gaze on.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Queen.</speaker>
                     <l>We find the <hi>Eunuch</hi> fit for our Employments,</l>
                     <l>Therefore I will unclapſe my Soul to thee;</l>
                     <l>I've always found thee Truſty, and I Love thee.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Eunuch.</speaker>
                     <l>With thanks I ever muſt acknowledge it,</l>
                     <l>And lay my Life at my great Miſtreſs's feet</l>
                     <l>To ſpend it when ſhe pleaſe.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Queen.</speaker>
                     <l>We need it not</l>
                     <l>As yet, <hi>Caſtrato,</hi> but we may hereafter.</l>
                     <l>See there's the Platform of great <hi>Childricks</hi> Death;</l>
                     <l>And they which muſt be thought his Murderers,</l>
                     <l>Our Enemies, and now new Courtiers;</l>
                     <pb n="6" facs="tcp:57541:6"/>
                     <l> Whom hitherto I have reſerv'd for Policy;</l>
                     <l>Firſt, that they take away the Guilt from us;</l>
                     <l>Next, being apprehended, ſtudied Deaths,</l>
                     <l>The Heads of all our Engineers ſhall' ſit</l>
                     <l>To invent unheard of Torments for the Slaves;</l>
                     <l>I long to ſee them here, here in this frame,</l>
                     <l>Greeting their Kindreds Bones.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Eunuch.</speaker>
                     <p>Moſt Excellent!</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Queen.</speaker>
                     <l>Then I'le commend thee to my Elder Son,</l>
                     <l>Where thou ſhalt wind into his Secret Thoughts;</l>
                     <l>As for the Younger Boy let me alone;</l>
                     <l>And when we have them on the Hip, they ſhall</l>
                     <l>Follow their Father unto Hells black Hall.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Eunuch.</speaker>
                     <p>You are the Goddeſs of invention.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Queen.</speaker>
                     <l>Will not this be Brave? Ha! how likeſt thou it!</l>
                     <l>Now by this Light I'me taken ſtrangely with thee;</l>
                     <l>Kiſs me, Kiſs me, cloſer Villain:</l>
                     <l>Fie! what a <hi>January</hi> Lip thou haſt,</l>
                     <l>A pair of Iſickles; ſure thou haſt bought</l>
                     <l>A pair of Eaſt Lips of the Chaſt <hi>Diana's;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Thy Blood's meer Snow broth: Kiſs me again.</l>
                     <l>Now ſee if you can find theſe Gallants forth,</l>
                     <l>And bring them to our preſence.</l>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>Exit</hi> Eunuch, <hi>and Enter</hi> Landrey.</stage>
                     <l>Oh <hi>Landrey!</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Your Viſits have been freer, but I grow Old,</l>
                     <l>And you Command the Beauties of the time.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Landrey.</speaker>
                     <l>What means my Noble Miſtreſs? think you the Blood</l>
                     <l>Runs ſo degenerate within theſe Veins,</l>
                     <l>To ſtoop to an inferiouſ Embrace,</l>
                     <l>When I enjoy the beſt?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Queen.</speaker>
                     <l>We are Betray'd.</l>
                     <l>I'le tell thee a good jeſt <hi>Landrey,</hi> wilt hear it?</l>
                     <l>This Morning dreſſing my Head, my Husband came,</l>
                     <l>And with his Switch, for he was then to Hunt,</l>
                     <l>A Gentle ſtroke he gave me on the back;</l>
                     <l>My fancy buſied then to make me fine,</l>
                     <l>Suppoſing it was you that ſported ſo;</l>
                     <l>Cry'd, my <hi>Landrey,</hi> in Story we ſtill find,</l>
                     <l>The beſt Knights ſtrike before, and not behind:</l>
                     <l>The King who always underſtood too faſt,</l>
                     <l>Quits ſuddenly my Chamber, what he intends</l>
                     <l>I cannot gueſs, unleſs it be our Deaths,</l>
                     <l>Which if he ſpeedily perform not, then</l>
                     <l>Know he ſhall never, for this Night concludes him;</l>
                     <pb n="7" facs="tcp:57541:6"/>
                     <l> My Sons I weigh not, thus, they have Rebell'd,</l>
                     <l>And taken Spirit of late to oppoſe my, will,</l>
                     <l>And contradict my Pleaſure in thy Love,</l>
                     <l>For which it is not ſafe that they ſhould Live;</l>
                     <l>The Kingdoms Heir ſhall be a Child of thine,</l>
                     <l>And Kings and Queens ſhall follow in thy Line.</l>
                     <l>Oh! are they come, they're welcome, take our word,</l>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>Enter</hi> Lam, <hi>&amp;</hi> Dum. <hi>very brave, &amp; the</hi> Eunuch.</stage>
                     <l>A Queens word, <hi>Fredegonde</hi> bids ye welcome</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Both.</speaker>
                     <p>Your Highneſs is as full of Grace as Mercy.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Queen.</speaker>
                     <l>Riſe and follow us, we'le be your Guardian,</l>
                     <l>And Protectreſs.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Landrey.</speaker>
                     <p>Madam, who are theſe?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Queen.</speaker>
                     <l>Sheep for my Shambles, whom I have fatted up</l>
                     <l>Only for Slaughter; Things are on foot decreed,</l>
                     <l>Shall make ſome Smile to Night, and others Bloed.</l>
                     <stage>Exeunt Omnes.</stage>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="scene">
                  <head>SCENE <hi>III.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Clovis <hi>at one Door,</hi> Aphelia <hi>and a Page with a Light at the Other.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clovis.</speaker>
                     <l>My beſt Miſtreſs, what Angel brought you hither;</l>
                     <l>For I know my Lions attend your goodneſs?</l>
                     <l>Why weep you? Truſt me your Eyes ſeed pearl,</l>
                     <l>Bracelets for Gods to wear about their Arms.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Aphelia.</speaker>
                     <l>I am too fond, yet he Swears he Loves me,</l>
                     <l>I have believ'd him too, for I have found <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </l>
                     <l>A God-like Nature in him, and a Truth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </l>
                     <l>Hitherto Conſtant. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clov.</speaker>
                     <p>Gentleſt Sweet, the Cauſe?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Aphelia.</speaker>
                     <l>If this ſhould be diſſembled, not your Heart,</l>
                     <l>And having won my Souls affection,</l>
                     <l>Should on a Judgment more retired to State,</l>
                     <l>Fling off affection, and leave me in Love,</l>
                     <l>What Ill-bred-tales the World would make of me?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clov.</speaker>
                     <l>That Jelouſy I'le ſtrangle, take this Ring</l>
                     <l>As I that Diamond dazled by thine Eyes,</l>
                     <l>Whoſe Beauties Sickned' cauſe Eclips'd by thine</l>
                     <l>Be theſe the mutual Pledges of our Love,</l>
                     <l>Our Marriage before our Marriage,</l>
                     <pb n="8" facs="tcp:57541:7"/>
                     <l> And curſed be they that Seperate our Love,</l>
                     <l>Tho' <hi>France</hi> be one, or, what is greater, <hi>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                              <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                           </gap>.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Are yor fears over now?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Aphe.</speaker>
                     <l>I dare no Ill,</l>
                     <l>And therefore doubt none.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clov.</speaker>
                     <p>Heark! The King is coming.</p>
                     <stage>A Floriſh.</stage>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> King, Queen, Clotaire, Landrey, Dumaine, Lamot, <hi>Ladies and Attendance; with the Guard, and</hi> Eunuch.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>King.</speaker>
                     <l>Approach our Perſon nearer, for methinks</l>
                     <l>Y'ave honeſt faces, if your Hearts keep touch</l>
                     <l>To your outward Semblance, y'are a pair</l>
                     <l>Nothing but Death ſhall force from me.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Queen.</speaker>
                     <l>Good, Good!</l>
                     <l>This Phyſick works.</l>
                     <stage>Aſide.</stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Eunuch.</speaker>
                     <p>Beſt Madam, is it done?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Queeen.</speaker>
                     <l>I my Black Genius, ſuch a fatal Dram</l>
                     <l>I have adminiſter'd, will wing his Soul</l>
                     <l>With expedition to the other World:</l>
                     <l>His parts Eſſential, like a wearied Ghoſt</l>
                     <l>This Night forſakes his Inn, whence fled and gone,</l>
                     <l>Who knows where it ſhall lodge? Mark his looks,</l>
                     <l>See'ſt thou not Death thron'd in his hollow Eye?</l>
                     <l>Great Tyrant over Nature: See, obſerve.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Eunuch.</speaker>
                     <l>With looks inquiſitive I have beheld him,</l>
                     <l>But can perceive no alteration.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Queen.</speaker>
                     <l>Thou art a Fool, and want'ſt the optique nerves</l>
                     <l>To pry into my Acts; where I lay trains</l>
                     <l>Death comes before the grief; The Sulpherous Match</l>
                     <l>Deſtroys the Powder with a motion ſlow</l>
                     <l>To what I work with: As <hi>Antumns</hi> aged Leaf,</l>
                     <l>In youth the prime and glory of the wood,</l>
                     <l>Not to be graſpt by hand, falls with a puff,</l>
                     <l>And what we could not touch but now, we tread on.</l>
                     <l>So <hi>Childricke.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>King.</speaker>
                     <l>Oh! Lend me thine Arm <hi>Dumaine,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <stage>Dum. <hi>and</hi> Lam. <hi>both buſy about the King.</hi>
                     </stage>
                     <l>I know not what, but on the ſudden, ſomething—</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
                     <l>How the Nat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>-play and buz about the flame</l>
                     <l>That muſt Conſume them.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Eunuch.</speaker>
                     <p>Obſervant Coxcombs!</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clotaire.</speaker>
                     <l>What Star's Unſpher'd and walks upon the Earth,</l>
                     <l>Making our Night a Noon? methinks her ſight</l>
                     <l>Does Cute Blindneſs, and lends darkneſs Light.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Caſtrate.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <pb n="9" facs="tcp:57541:7"/>
                     <speaker>Eunuch.</speaker>
                     <p>Huſh! We are obſerved, My Lord.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clotaire.</speaker>
                     <p>What Lady's that?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Eunuch.</speaker>
                     <l>Which, that French India,</l>
                     <l>Who Sweats under the Pride ſhe bears about her.</l>
                     <l>She with whom your Brother holds diſcourſe?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clotaire.</speaker>
                     <p>That!</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Eun.</speaker>
                     <p>The Chaſt and Beautiful <hi>Aphelia.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clot.</speaker>
                     <l>Moſt true, Nature has much befriended her;</l>
                     <l>Art ſure ſhe's Honeſt?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Eun.</speaker>
                     <l>Snow's not purer Sir,</l>
                     <l>No Veſtal Virgin at the Altar hears</l>
                     <l>A Soul ſo incorrupt, ſo void of flame</l>
                     <l>That's looſly active.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clot.</speaker>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Eunuch,</hi> be our ſelf;</l>
                     <l>Get but that Lady for me, thou conceiveſt—</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Eun.</speaker>
                     <l>She dotes upon you Brother, through his means</l>
                     <l>I'le think upon ſome Plot.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clot.</speaker>
                     <p>Lend me thine Ear.</p>
                     <stage>They Whiſper.</stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>King.</speaker>
                     <l>Deſer our paſtimes paſtimes till another Night,</l>
                     <l>I am not well at eaſe.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Dum.</speaker>
                     <p>Lights for the King.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Eun.</speaker>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Dumaine</hi> be wiſe, thy foot is in the Snare,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Fredegonde</hi> hunts, an when ſhe hunts, beware.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Dum.</speaker>
                     <p>Wel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> warn'd half arm'd.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lam.</speaker>
                     <p>What ſays the Slave, <hi>Dumaine?</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Dum.</speaker>
                     <p>No matter what, mind we his Majeſty.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Queen.</speaker>
                     <p>My Royal Husband.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>King.</speaker>
                     <l>There is an <hi>Aetna</hi> in me,</l>
                     <l>The Air I draw returns illuminate.</l>
                     <l>Phyloſophy, thy Element of fire's here.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>
                        <hi>Clot.</hi> and <hi>Clov.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>How fares our Father?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>King.</speaker>
                     <l>Oh I Burn!</l>
                     <l>Fire, <hi>Veſuvius, Aetna, Veſuvius.</hi>—.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Queen.</speaker>
                     <l>His grace grows worſe and worſe, O my griev'd Heart!</l>
                     <l>Support him Gently Friends, Gently, Gently.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Exit. Om. ma.</hi> Eu. <hi>and</hi> Aphelia.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Aphe.</speaker>
                     <l>I credit your report and will obey,</l>
                     <l>His mind is Honourable, like his Parentage,</l>
                     <l>His Single name has arm'd me, pray lead on.</l>
                     <stage>A Screch with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in of all together Oh! Oh! Oh!</stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Eun.</speaker>
                     <l>Heark Lady! There was a fearfull ſound,</l>
                     <l>I ſear the King's departed, let's withdraw.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="scene">
                  <pb n="10" facs="tcp:57541:8"/>
                  <head>SCENE <hi>IV.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Lamot, <hi>and the Guard.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lamot.</speaker>
                     <p>O woe! woe! woe!</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clot.</speaker>
                     <p>Horror and Death!</p>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>Enter</hi> Clotaire.</stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clov.</speaker>
                     <p>O diſmal, fatal Hour! <hi>Enter</hi> Clovis.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Queen, Dumaine, Landrey, Ladies, <hi>and the reſt of the Guard.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Queen.</speaker>
                     <p>With <hi>Childrick,</hi> end the World.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Dum.</speaker>
                     <p>Have Patience gentle Queen.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Queen.</speaker>
                     <l>Stand off,</l>
                     <l>Preach Patience to the Sea, when the rude Wind</l>
                     <l>Swells her ambitious Billows above the Clouds;</l>
                     <l>And if thou Tutoreſt them to Peace and Silence,</l>
                     <l>I'le be as Calm as they.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clot.</speaker>
                     <l>The Treaſon here,</l>
                     <l>And not the Traytor, quite confounds my Senſes,</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Queen.</speaker>
                     <l>Ignorance, dark as Hell; doubt ye the Traytors</l>
                     <l>I've brought a pair of Vipers to the Court,</l>
                     <l>Warm'd and reliev'd them with a ſting to Kill us,</l>
                     <l>Who could be author of this deed but they?</l>
                     <l>His new Boſom'd Friends have ſlain him.—</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clot.</speaker>
                     <l>Our Guard,</l>
                     <l>Lay Hands upon the Traytors.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Dum.</speaker>
                     <l>O <hi>Lamot!</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>We are betray'd, baſely beſet with Snares.</l>
                     <stage>They fight back to back againſt the Gu. &amp; ſeape.</stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lam.</speaker>
                     <p>Juſtice fight thou my cauſe with thine own Sword.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
                     <l>O Villains! would you let them ſcape? two Men</l>
                     <l>To paſs the ſtrength of our undaunted Guard;</l>
                     <l>This made my Soul, this grates my very Gall</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>King.</speaker>
                     <l>Make after them, and bring them back again;</l>
                     <l>Or by my Fathers Soul ye breath your laſt</l>
                     <l>Still art thou here <hi>Aphelia?</hi> Ha! I may</l>
                     <l>Uſe my Commanding Power now—Lead on;</l>
                     <l>Come Mother, Brother, Friends, pray let us go.</l>
                     <l>King ne're receiv'd a Crown ſo full of woe.</l>
                     <stage>Exeunt Omnes.</stage>
                  </sp>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="act">
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:57541:8"/>
               <head>ACT <hi>II.</hi>
               </head>
               <div n="1" type="scene">
                  <head>SCENE <hi>I.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter Old</hi> Briſſac <hi>and his Page, with a Taper.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Briſſac.</speaker>
                     <p>IS ſhe not come from Court yet?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Page.</speaker>
                     <l>No my Lord.</l>
                     <l>I loſt her mid'ſt the amazed multitude;</l>
                     <l>Where doubtleſs frighted with the ſudden horror,</l>
                     <l>She has with other beauties of the Court</l>
                     <l>Retired her ſelf untill the Morning-Star.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Briſ.</speaker>
                     <l>'Tis very likely ſo! Yet do ye hear,</l>
                     <l>Call up your Fellows; I'le not to Bed to Night,</l>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>Exit</hi> Page, <hi>&amp; Enter pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently with</hi> 2 <hi>Serving-men.</hi>
                     </stage>
                     <l>My thoughts are full of Tempeſt, diſmal thinkings;</l>
                     <l>Where is my Son? Why went He not to Court?</l>
                     <l>Perhaps ſome Sacrilegious hands have ſeiz'd on her;</l>
                     <l>Courts are no Sanctuaries, ſhe's no Veſtal:</l>
                     <l>May be ſhe's ſafe, then why returns ſhe not?</l>
                     <l>Why ſends ſhe not glad Meſſengers of Health!</l>
                     <l>No! No! She's loſt, and I undone for ever!</l>
                     <l>Run to the Court, they move not, why ſo faſt?</l>
                     <l>Let me deliberate; that were to give</l>
                     <l>The Courtiers notice I have loſt my Daughter,</l>
                     <l>Whom they will then ſuſpect, and call her fame</l>
                     <l>Into an Ill conſtruction; No! no! no!</l>
                     <l>O my poor Daughter, my <hi>Aphelia!</hi>
                     </l>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>Enter</hi> Charles Briſſac <hi>and</hi> Clovis <hi>Muf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fled in his Cloak.</hi>
                     </stage>
                     <l>Oh Sir you'r welcome, where's your Siſter,</l>
                     <l>I muſt have her Sirrah and I will,</l>
                     <l>Where is ſhe, <hi>Charles,</hi> where is ſhe?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Char.</speaker>
                     <p>My Honoured Father,—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Briſ.</speaker>
                     <l>Tut, Tut, Honour me no Honour,</l>
                     <l>Nor Father me no Father!</l>
                     <l>Where i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> your Siſter, Sirrah?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Charles.</speaker>
                     <p>My Siſter!</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Briſ.</speaker>
                     <p>Your Siſter!</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Charles.</speaker>
                     <l>Within Sir, otherwiſe this Gentleman</l>
                     <l>Has loſt his Labour; he's come to Viſit her.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Briſ.</speaker>
                     <l>Hoyday, Hoyday, Hoyday! to Viſit her?</l>
                     <l>Plots, Plots, meer fetches; to Viſit her!</l>
                     <l>What at the dead of Night? when the whole World</l>
                     <l>Is Sunk in ſlumber, and our Luſty Youth,</l>
                     <pb n="12" facs="tcp:57541:9"/>
                     <l> As quiet as the Grave; to Viſit her!</l>
                     <l>O moſt ridiculous! to Viſit her!</l>
                     <l>Pray Gentleman conſider, does your Siſter keep</l>
                     <l>Times ſo Prepoſterous for Viſits in?</l>
                     <l>Makes ſhe a day of Night; or has ſhe been breed</l>
                     <l>As looſe as <hi>Lais,</hi> to love Night-Courtings?</l>
                     <l>Do not diſtract me thus, to Viſit her!</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Char.</speaker>
                     <l>Pray Sir collect your ſelf, this Gentleman</l>
                     <l>Even at that Horrid point where the King, fell—</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Briſ.</speaker>
                     <l>Why look you now, there is more Miſchief toward;</l>
                     <l>What a World is this?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Char.</speaker>
                     <l>Saw a Ring drop off my Siſters ſinger,</l>
                     <l>Which he had then deliver'd, but that fright</l>
                     <l>Which renders men forgetfull, made him ſo;</l>
                     <l>But knowing where ſhe lived, (ſo he proteſts)</l>
                     <l>He would not Sleep until it were delivered.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Briſ.</speaker>
                     <l>Pray let me ſee the Ring; Yes it was hers,</l>
                     <l>And ſhe would ſay, ſhe'd never part with it</l>
                     <l>But when ſhe meant to Wed, if you have Married her</l>
                     <l>Or have her promiſe rivited to yours,</l>
                     <l>Tell me but where ſhe is, I'le be content,</l>
                     <l>For I in loſing her, have loſt my ſelf.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clov.</speaker>
                     <p>O my Prophetique Soul, then 'tis no Idle fear.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Char.</speaker>
                     <p>How! The Monſieur, what makes he here?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clov.</speaker>
                     <l>There's ſomething whiſpers me, go not to Bed,</l>
                     <l>Go not to Bed till thou haſt found her out:</l>
                     <l>Beeſt thou my Gonious, or what Powers elſe,</l>
                     <l>Suggeſting lawfull things I will obey thee.</l>
                     <l>Sleep ever-waking Envy and Miſtruſt,</l>
                     <l>Yet things that never knew what Slumber meant;</l>
                     <l>Ghoſts keep your Beds, ye Centinels of Night,</l>
                     <l>Goblins and Specters do not walk your round,</l>
                     <l>A general Lethargy Seize on this Hour,</l>
                     <l>Yet I alone the Watchman of this Night,</l>
                     <l>Will wake in ſpite of Fate. <hi>Argus</hi> thine Eyes</l>
                     <l>To find <hi>Aphelia</hi> and her Miſeries.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Exit.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Briſ.</speaker>
                     <l>Pritty, in good ſadneſs, wond'rous pritty,</l>
                     <l>Is he in earneſt?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Char.</speaker>
                     <l>Sure he diſſembles not.</l>
                     <l>I little dreamt when I did let him In,</l>
                     <l>What Perſon grac<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>d our Threſhold.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Briſ.</speaker>
                     <l>Ha Sirrah!</l>
                     <l>What a Girl's this to be out o'th' way?</l>
                     <l>He's in Love that's certain, Let me ſee.</l>
                     <pb n="13" facs="tcp:57541:9"/>
                     <l> When I was firſt a Lover as he is,</l>
                     <l>I'de juſt ſuch cold fegaries in my Brain,</l>
                     <l>Such Midnight madneſs. This puling Baggage</l>
                     <l>May loſe her ſelf for ever, and her Fortunes,</l>
                     <l>For this Hours abſence, go, be gone,</l>
                     <l>Follow his Royal Perſon, Comfort him,</l>
                     <l>Tell him my Daughter will again be found,</l>
                     <l>And ſo good Angels grant we meet with her.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Exe. one at one door and the other at the other.</stage>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="scene">
                  <head>SCENE <hi>II.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Eunuch <hi>lighting</hi> Aphelia.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Aphe.</speaker>
                     <l>Into what Laberinth do you lead me Sir?</l>
                     <l>What perplexed by-ways? I ſhould fear,</l>
                     <l>Had you not us'd his Name, which is to me</l>
                     <l>A Strengh 'gainſt Terror; and himſelf ſo good,</l>
                     <l>Occaſion cannot vary, nor the Night,</l>
                     <l>Youth nor his wild deſire; Otherwiſe</l>
                     <l>A Si<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>nt Sorrow from mine Eyes would ſteal,</l>
                     <l>And tell ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>d Stories for me.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Eunu.</speaker>
                     <l>Do not fear,</l>
                     <l>You are too tender of your Honour, Lady,</l>
                     <l>Too full of agaiſh trembling; the Noble Prince</l>
                     <l>Is as <hi>December</hi> froſty in deſire,</l>
                     <l>Save what is Lawfull, he not owns that cheat,</l>
                     <l>Which were you Snow, would thew a tear from you.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Aphe.</speaker>
                     <p>This is the place appointed.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Eunu.</speaker>
                     <l>I'le go call him,</l>
                     <l>In the mean time, pleaſe you to reſt your ſelf,</l>
                     <l>Here is a Little Book will bear you Company</l>
                     <stage>Gives her a book, ſhe ſits down and reads.</stage>
                     <l>'Till I return, which will be ſuddenly</l>
                     <l>Now <hi>Eunuch</hi> muſt the Artumie of Wit,</l>
                     <l>From the dull Mixture of theſe leaden Brains</l>
                     <l>Extract the Elixir of pure Villany.</l>
                     <l>Hither I'le ſend the King, not that I mean</l>
                     <l>To give him leave to cool his burning Luſt,</l>
                     <l>For <hi>Clovis</hi> ſhall prevent him in the Fact;</l>
                     <l>And thus I ſhall Endear my ſelf to both:</l>
                     <pb n="14" facs="tcp:57541:10"/>
                     <l> 
                        <hi>Clovis</hi> Enrag'd perhaps will kill the King,</l>
                     <l>Or by the King will periſh; if both fall,</l>
                     <l>Or either, both ways makes for me.</l>
                     <l>The Queen as rootedly does hate her Sons,</l>
                     <l>As I her Ladiſhip; to ſee this fray</l>
                     <l>She muſt be brought by me. It ſhall be ſo;</l>
                     <l>Her breath will ſtir in them confuſed Storms,</l>
                     <l>In midſt of whoſe wild rage, the Court will ſeem</l>
                     <l>A <hi>G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>lgoth<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>e</hi> of Miſchief; for her ſake</l>
                     <l>I'le ſay I ſet on foot this hopefull brawl,</l>
                     <l>Whilſt ſhe will Hug, and Kiſs me for the ſame:</l>
                     <l>Thus on all ſides, the <hi>Eunuch</hi> will play foul,</l>
                     <stage>Exit.</stage>
                     <l>And as his face is black, he'l have his Soul.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Aphe.</speaker>
                     <l>Poor raviſh'd <hi>Philomel,</hi> thy lot was ill</l>
                     <stage>She leaves reading.</stage>
                     <l>To meet that Violence in a Brother,</l>
                     <l>Which I in a Stranger doubt: Yet methinks</l>
                     <l>I am too Confident, for I feel my heart</l>
                     <l>Burthen'd with ſomething ominous; theſe men,</l>
                     <l>Are things of Subtle Nature, and their Oaths</l>
                     <l>Unconſtant as themſelves—Let me proceed.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clot.</speaker>
                     <l>Methinks I ſtand like <hi>Tarquin</hi> in that Night</l>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>Enter</hi> Clo. <hi>Muſſled.</hi>
                     </stage>
                     <l>When he defiled the Chaſtity of <hi>Rome,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Doubtfull of what to do, and like a Thief</l>
                     <l>I take each noiſe for an Officer.</l>
                     <l>Tho' I do know it is a deed of Death,</l>
                     <l>Condemned for Torments in the other World,</l>
                     <l>Such tempting ſweetneſs dwells on every Limb,</l>
                     <l>That I muſt venture my Eſſential parts</l>
                     <l>For the fruition of a moments Luſt:</l>
                     <l>Oh Pleaſure dearly bought.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Aphe.</speaker>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Clovis</hi> may prove unkind, alack why not?</l>
                     <l>He's but a man. Say he ſhould offer foul,</l>
                     <l>The Evil Counſel of a Secret Place,</l>
                     <l>and Night his Friend, may out-tempt his will:</l>
                     <l>I dare not ſtand the Hazzard, Guide me Light</l>
                     <l>To ſome Untrodden Place, where poor I may,</l>
                     <l>Wear out the Night with ſighs till it be day.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clot.</speaker>
                     <l>I muſt be bold and reſolute; Sweet Maid,</l>
                     <stage>He meets her.</stage>
                     <l>Fair, Virtuous Damſel, Hail.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Aphe.</speaker>
                     <l>What man art thou,</l>
                     <l>That doſt thy Countenance bury in thy Cloak,</l>
                     <l>And hideſt they face from Darkneſs and the Night?</l>
                     <l>If thine intents deſerve a Muſler too,</l>
                     <l>And that thy thoughts dare non allow themſelves.</l>
                     <pb n="15" facs="tcp:57541:10"/>
                     <l> Withdraw, and Act them not, what art thou? ſpeak,</l>
                     <l>And wherefore cam'ſt thou hither?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clot.</speaker>
                     <l>Wouldſt thou know?</l>
                     <l>I came to find one Beautiful as thou,</l>
                     <l>And am a man willing to pleaſe a Woman.</l>
                     <l>Nay, nay, you muſt not leave mo thus.</l>
                     <stage>She profers to go off.</stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Aphe.</speaker>
                     <p>Muſt not.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clot.</speaker>
                     <p>No, muſt not, 'tis I that ſpeaks it Lady.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Aphe.</speaker>
                     <p>I know thee not.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cloth.</speaker>
                     <l>But I muſt you, yes and the right way too,</l>
                     <l>Which is th' acquaintance ſureſt.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Aphe.</speaker>
                     <p>Help, Help, Help!</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clot.</speaker>
                     <l>Nay, nay, nay, none of your Prick-Songs Lady,</l>
                     <l>If you riſe a Note, or beat the Air with Clamour,</l>
                     <l>You ſee your Death.</l>
                     <stage>Draws his Dagger</stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Aphe.</speaker>
                     <l>What Violence is this?</l>
                     <l>Why do you threaten War, fright my ſoft peace</l>
                     <l>With moſt ungentle Steel, what have I done</l>
                     <l>Dangerous, or am like to do? why do you wrack me thus?</l>
                     <stage>pulls her along.</stage>
                     <l>Mine Arms are Guilty of no crime, do not torment 'em,</l>
                     <l>My Hands and they have joyn'd in Prayer together</l>
                     <l>For mankind that is Holy; if in that Act</l>
                     <l>They have not Pray'd for you, mend and be good,</l>
                     <l>The fault is none of theirs.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clot.</speaker>
                     <l>You gueſs my Mind</l>
                     <l>What Earthquake ſhakes you thu?</l>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>She trembles as ama<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ed.</hi>
                     </stage>
                     <l>Come do not ſeem more Holy then you are,</l>
                     <l>I know your Heart.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Aphe.</speaker>
                     <l>Let your Dagger too, Noble Sir ſtrike home,</l>
                     <l>And Sacrifice Soul to Chaſtity,</l>
                     <l>As white and ſpotleſs as her Innocence</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clot.</speaker>
                     <p>This is not the way.— Know you me Beauty?</p>
                     <stage>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 line">
                           <desc>〈1 line〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Aphe.</speaker>
                     <p>The King!</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clot.</speaker>
                     <p>The ſame, Riſe up and put off ſear.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Aphe.</speaker>
                     <l>I dare not ſear, it's Treaſon to ſuſpect</l>
                     <l>My King can think an Ill, worſe to Act it:</l>
                     <l>I know you'r God like good, and have but try'd</l>
                     <l>How far weak Woman durſt be Virtuous</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clot.</speaker>
                     <l>Pritty Simplicity, thou art deceived:</l>
                     <l>Thy Wit as well as Beauty wounds me, and thy To<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                           <desc>•••</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </l>
                     <l>In pleading for thee, pleads againſt thy ſelf:</l>
                     <l>It is thy Virtue moves me, and thy Good,</l>
                     <l>Tempts me to Acts of Evil: wert thou bad,</l>
                     <l>Or looſe in thy deſires, I cou'd ſtand</l>
                     <pb n="16" facs="tcp:57541:11"/>
                     <l> And only Gaze, not Surfet on thy Beauty;</l>
                     <l>But as thou art, let me not ſee thy face,</l>
                     <l>I'me deſperate grown in Ill, and muſt enjoy</l>
                     <l>thee, or not thee thy Life.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Aphe.</speaker>
                     <l>I offer it.</l>
                     <l>You are my King and may Command my Life,</l>
                     <l>My will to Sin you cannot, you may force</l>
                     <l>Unſancted deeds upon me, Spot my fame,</l>
                     <l>And make my Body ſuffer, not my mind.</l>
                     <l>When you have done this irreligious deed,</l>
                     <l>What Trophy, or what Triumph will it bring,</l>
                     <l>More then a living Scorn upon your Name?</l>
                     <l>Do not believe this deed can lye conceal'd,</l>
                     <l>For Kings appear when they are Thron'd in Sin,</l>
                     <l>Like to prodigious Creatures in the Air,</l>
                     <l>At which all Tongues are mute, all Eyes do ſtare.</l>
                     <l>Is't not a Single Ill which you commit:</l>
                     <l>What in the Subject is a pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ty fault</l>
                     <l>Monſters your Actions, and's a ſoul offence:</l>
                     <l>You give your Subjects Licenſe to offend</l>
                     <l>When you do teach them how.</l>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>Enter</hi> Clovis <hi>and</hi> Charles.</stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clot.</speaker>
                     <l>Good, Ill apply'd:</l>
                     <stage>Aſide.</stage>
                     <l>I will endure no longer, come along,</l>
                     <l>Or by the curious Spinſtry of thy Head,</l>
                     <l>Which Nature's cunning'ſt ſinger twiſted out,</l>
                     <l>I'le drag thee to my Coach: Tempt not my fury.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clov.</speaker>
                     <l>Can I endure this; O my Salt Blood</l>
                     <l>Leap from my Boſom, up into the Air.</l>
                     <l>Unhand me <hi>Charles,</hi> and render me my ſelf,</l>
                     <l>Leſt I forget my ſelf on thee.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Char.</speaker>
                     <l>Great Prince,</l>
                     <l>Remember 'tis your Brother and the King.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clov.</speaker>
                     <l>Oh that I could forget it, and ſhake off</l>
                     <l>Duty at once, and Conſanguinity,</l>
                     <l>That like a Whirlwind I might ruſh upon him,</l>
                     <l>And bear him to Deſtruction—Monſter of men,</l>
                     <l>Thou King of Darkneſs, down unto thy Hell,</l>
                     <l>I have a Spell will lay thee, Honeſty,</l>
                     <l>And this abuſed Goodneſs: Is't not enough</l>
                     <l>That thou haſt wronged <hi>Crotilda,</hi> raviſht a Maid</l>
                     <l>A Virgin of that Purity of Life,</l>
                     <l>Might Saint Her here on Earth; but wilt thou add</l>
                     <l>Unto thy Firſt a Second Violence?</l>
                     <l>The Gods muſt not forgive!</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <pb n="17" facs="tcp:57541:11"/>
                     <speaker>Clot.</speaker>
                     <l>I deſpiſe thee;</l>
                     <l>If thou wouldſt gain our Love, be a Brother,</l>
                     <l>And aid me in my longings.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clov.</speaker>
                     <l>Be a man;</l>
                     <l>And ſhake a Nature off, that needs muſt damn thee:</l>
                     <l>O ſet a Period to Sins Progreſs here,</l>
                     <l>Proceed not in theſe Courſes, leſt you grow</l>
                     <l>As Great in Sin as Scepter.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clot.</speaker>
                     <l>Traytor, Boy!</l>
                     <l>Thy fate moves in thoſe words.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clov.</speaker>
                     <l>Is't even ſo;</l>
                     <l>Then Guard thy ſelf our King, for I am quick</l>
                     <l>As Lightning, or the thought that Executes.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Char.</speaker>
                     <l>Hold hold, my Lord, forbear; Call in more aid,</l>
                     <l>Ring out the Alarum-Bell, Call up the Court,</l>
                     <l>Beſtir thee <hi>Eunuch,</hi> whilſt interpoſe</l>
                     <l>My Body to the fury of the Storm.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Exit</hi> Eun. <hi>Alarum-Bell.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
                     <l>What means this ſudden out-cry? Oh my Sons!</l>
                     <l>Hold, Hold! Part them good Gentlemen.</l>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>Ent.</hi> Qu. <hi>&amp; Ladys Guard,</hi> Landrey</stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clot.</speaker>
                     <l>Mother you are a trouble, ſtand from mine Arm,</l>
                     <l>Let me cut off Rebellion in the Spring,</l>
                     <l>Leſt it beget a harveſt that will prove</l>
                     <l>Fruitfull in Treaſon, Brav'd by a Subjects hand.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
                     <l>Though Nature by Precedency of Birth,</l>
                     <l>Made thee his King, it therefore follows not</l>
                     <l>His Murtherer; wherein is our <hi>Clo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                              <desc>•••</desc>
                           </gap>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Greater then <hi>Clovis?</hi> Know, the ſelf-ſame Blood</l>
                     <l>That Spirits thee, makes him as Valiant,</l>
                     <l>The difference lies in <hi>Anno Domini.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Eun.</speaker>
                     <p>Accurate Miſchief, Fluent Villany.</p>
                     <stage>Aſide.</stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
                     <l>I grant thou art his Elder; by which Law</l>
                     <l>Thou art born his Subject, not his Equal, <hi>Clovis;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>For <hi>Clotaire</hi> is thy King, and Subjects hands,</l>
                     <l>Without the deep and dangerous Trayto<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> Name,</l>
                     <l>May not advance againſt their Sovereign, Head.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clot.</speaker>
                     <l>Neither ſhall his without correction:</l>
                     <l>Upon him Slaves.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
                     <l>Hold, I Command ye hold.</l>
                     <l>O <hi>Clotaire,</hi> thou art of a Valiant Soul,</l>
                     <l>And wilt thou baſely thus beſet thy Brother?</l>
                     <l>Fear Argues ſpirits moſt degenerate,</l>
                     <l>And that thou ſeareſt th'advantage argues i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </l>
                     <l>Oh ſet not on thy Slaves; if he muſt dye,</l>
                     <l>Let thy hand Sacrifice, not Butcher him.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <pb n="18" facs="tcp:57541:12"/>
                     <speaker>Clot.</speaker>
                     <p>That Argument Sounds harſh; ſhall <hi>Clotaire,</hi> fear?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Eun.</speaker>
                     <p>Exquiſite Philter, Poyſon to the height.</p>
                     <stage>Aſide.</stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clov.</speaker>
                     <p>Sacrifice me, it is not in his Power.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
                     <l>We hope ſo <hi>Clovis;</hi> yet thy Brother King,</l>
                     <l>Is as an Earthly-God, his Will, his Law,</l>
                     <l>His Power uncircumſcrib'd, unlimited,</l>
                     <l>For Kings have will as uncontroul'd as fate,</l>
                     <l>And Majeſty can look a Subject dead.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clov.</speaker>
                     <p>How look me Dead? I do not fear his frown<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
                     <l>I Grant thee as great a <hi>Baſaliske</hi> as he;</l>
                     <l>As he is meetly man: but as thy King,</l>
                     <l>Divinity does prop him; he ſtands ſure</l>
                     <l>That builds on that Foundation: Yet I know</l>
                     <l>Thy Sword's as Sharp as his, and where it lights</l>
                     <l>Imprints as much of fate, thine Arm as ſtrong,</l>
                     <l>Thy Spirit as daring, and thy will as prompt</l>
                     <l>To any Action that may right a man.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clot.</speaker>
                     <l>He is your Darling, you do well to praiſe him;</l>
                     <l>When I have ſlain him, Write his Epitaph.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clov.</speaker>
                     <l>My Epitaph, this Pen of Steel ſhall firſt,</l>
                     <l>Write on thy Heart, thine end.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
                     <l>It Operates.</l>
                     <l>The Venom'd Potion of a Womans Tongue</l>
                     <l>Is more ſublim'd then Mercury.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clot.</speaker>
                     <l>Our Guard</l>
                     <l>That let's a Traytor pull me by the heard:</l>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>They fall upon him with th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>r Halberts and he's Slain.</hi>
                     </stage>
                     <l>Cut him to peices Raſcalls.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
                     <l>O my Son!</l>
                     <l>Villain, thy Hands have made theſe holes, for which</l>
                     <l>The winged Vengeance of a Mothers Curſe</l>
                     <l>Subtler in Operation then Lightning,</l>
                     <l>Strike thro' thy Body every Limb a Death.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
                     <l>How cunningly ſhe ſpits her Poyſon forth,</l>
                     <l>I know her Soul is Light, ſhe's glad he's Dead,</l>
                     <l>And joys in the opportunity to Curſe the killer;</l>
                     <l>For which ſhe gains the name of Pious Mother:</l>
                     <l>Here's pritty Woman Villain, diſſimulation.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Aph.</speaker>
                     <l>If they have ſlain him, wherefore do I Live?</l>
                     <l>O my ſwoln'n Heart.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clot.</speaker>
                     <l>Bear hence theſe Corps, withall</l>
                     <l>Remove that Syren from our wandring Eyes,</l>
                     <stage>Landrey <hi>and</hi> 2 <hi>or</hi> 3 <hi>Lords more ſeem to Sollicite for</hi> Aph.</stage>
                     <l>And Cage her in a Dungeon, hence begone,</l>
                     <l>Bear her to Priſon, reaſon not the Cauſe</l>
                     <l>A Kings Prerogative's above his Laws.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Exit.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <pb n="19" facs="tcp:57541:12"/>
                     <speaker>Aph.</speaker>
                     <l>Be mercifull, and lead to Death, away;</l>
                     <l>Since he is gone, it is to Dye, to ſtay.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Exeunt Omnes, manen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> Queen, Landrey, Eun.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
                     <l>Now we begin to ſlouriſh, this black Night</l>
                     <l>Is only lighted by our ſtars, that ſmile</l>
                     <l>Upon theſe actions, and rejoyce to ſee</l>
                     <l>Thee our ſole Favouſite ſo near a Crown:</l>
                     <l>But tell me <hi>Landrey,</hi> how did I play the Mother?</l>
                     <l>Did not I preſent a <hi>Niobe,</hi> in paſſion,</l>
                     <l>Did'ſt thou not fear an Inundation.</l>
                     <l>A deluge of Salt Rhume?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Land.</speaker>
                     <l>You had no coſtive Eye, that I dare ſay,</l>
                     <l>For certainly you wept.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
                     <l>Yes; as a good Actor in a Play would do,</l>
                     <l>Whoſe fancy works as if he waking dreamt</l>
                     <l>So ſtrongly on the object that it Copes with,</l>
                     <l>Shaping realities from Mockeries;</l>
                     <l>And ſo the Queen did weep: By this good Light</l>
                     <l>I think I could become the Stage as well</l>
                     <l>As any ſhe that ſells her Breath in publick.</l>
                     <l>Come ſhall we Act <hi>Landrey?</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Land.</speaker>
                     <l>Act great Lady;</l>
                     <l>What Play ſhall we Enact?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
                     <l>Dull <hi>Landrey,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Nothing that's new, Old Plays you know are beſt:</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Eunuch</hi> is our Bed ready.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
                     <p>Great Queen it is.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
                     <l>Come then my Joy to Bed, where we will ſport,</l>
                     <l>And laugh at Death, which Triumphs in the Court.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Exeunt Mane<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> Eunuch.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
                     <l>Go ſleep your laſt; I'le ſtraight unto the King,</l>
                     <l>And he ſhall take them in the very Act;</l>
                     <l>And then to Cover my Diſcovery</l>
                     <l>I'le ſet on fire the Queens Bed-Chamber,</l>
                     <l>That ſo I may diſturb them more ſecure,</l>
                     <l>And yet the Plot not mine: I'le tell the King</l>
                     <l>Unleſs he preſent Help, his Mother burns.</l>
                     <l>About is then, this is a happy Night;</l>
                     <l>The more it works their Woe, more's my delight</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Exit.</stage>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="act">
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:57541:13"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>ACT</hi> III.</head>
               <div n="1" type="scene">
                  <head>SCENE <hi>I.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter the</hi> King <hi>and</hi> Eunuch.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Eun.</speaker>
                     <l>LOok how it flames! I fear ſome Treachery;</l>
                     <l>Beat at her Chamber-door, cry it aloud,</l>
                     <stage>Knocks at the Door.</stage>
                     <l>And let your Voice be Thunder to this Lightning.</l>
                     <l>Cry Fire, Fire, Fire! The Court is all a Hot-houſe.</l>
                     <l>Fire, Fire, Fire!</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clot.</speaker>
                     <l>Great Queen, Royal Mother, open your door,</l>
                     <l>Leſt you do ſleep for ever, Mother awake.</l>
                     <l>The God of ſleep lies heavy on her Eyes.</l>
                     <l>Force open the door, Fire, Fire, Fire!</l>
                     <stage>again.</stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Eun.</speaker>
                     <l>It's fortified 'gainſt ſtrength, you muſt call lowder.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clot.</speaker>
                     <l>Mother, Queen, Mother, awake, awake!</l>
                     <l>Your ſleep was never liker death then now:</l>
                     <l>Lady, Great Princes, Fire, Fire, Fire!</l>
                     <stage>again.</stage>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Queen <hi>above in Night attire and</hi> Landrey.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
                     <l>What Sawcy Groom</l>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>Exit</hi> Eunuch.</stage>
                     <l>Beats our offenceleſs doors thus daringly,</l>
                     <l>He'd better rous'd a ſleeping Lioneſs,</l>
                     <l>Then thus to have broke our ſlumbers.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clot.</speaker>
                     <l>Look,</l>
                     <l>The Fire will give you Light, 'tis I your Son;</l>
                     <l>Ely from that Chamber, elſe you are but dead,</l>
                     <l>Your Court is all a bonefire.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
                     <l>Let it burn.</l>
                     <l>I've loſt my Credit everlaſtingly,</l>
                     <stage>aſide.</stage>
                     <l>I will not move a-foot.</l>
                     <stage>aloud.</stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clot.</speaker>
                     <l>You muſt be forced then.</l>
                     <stage>beats at the door.</stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Land.</speaker>
                     <l>Where are your wits now in neceſſity,</l>
                     <stage>Softly.</stage>
                     <l>We ſhall be taken, and you ſham'd for ever;</l>
                     <l>Bethink, Bethink your self.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
                     <l>I have't, it ſhall be ſo; there put on that,</l>
                     <l>Appearing in his Brothers Warlike Shape.</l>
                     <l>Thou wilt amaze, and ſo paſs by him ſafely.</l>
                     <stage>aſide.</stage>
                     <l>Do not appear to me, I did not wound thee;</l>
                     <stage>aloud.</stage>
                     <pb n="21" facs="tcp:57541:13"/>
                     <l> Seek out the Beds of thoſe that caus'd thy death,</l>
                     <l>And howl to them thy pittfull Complaint.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clot.</speaker>
                     <l>Whom do you hold diſcourſe with, with the Air?</l>
                     <l>Bethink your ſelf, this is not time to dally.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
                     <l>Oh, my Son, ſuch horrid apparitions, full of dread have I beheld, have quite unwitted me:</l>
                     <l>Your Brothers Ghoſt, fearfully terrible,</l>
                     <l>Has thr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                           <desc>•••</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>his diſmal night appear'd to me:</l>
                     <l>His Wou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                           <desc>•••</desc>
                        </gap> did bleed, juſt as our <hi>Clotaire</hi> caus'd them,</l>
                     <l>To thoſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> points, and calls <hi>Aphelia</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>To bear <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> companyi' th'other World,</l>
                     <l>Or elſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ightly haunt us in our ſleeps;</l>
                     <l>Thrice d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>y Revenge, and with that word</l>
                     <l>Sprang <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> the roof, which now ſtands bare to Heaven,</l>
                     <l>Where <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> did rain down fire which here we ſee.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clot.</speaker>
                     <p>Behold in comes.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Landrey <hi>in Armour.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
                     <p>Oh fear it not my Son.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clot.</speaker>
                     <l>What art thou that uſurp'ſt this dead of night</l>
                     <l>In me<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>tal like the ai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>? Why art thou ſent</l>
                     <l>To caſt a horror on me? If thy Soul</l>
                     <l>Walks unrevenged, and the grim Ferry-man</l>
                     <l>Deny thy paſſage, we'le perform thy rights;</l>
                     <l>Oh do not wound me with ſuch piteous ſigns</l>
                     <l>Leſt I diſſolve to air, and like thy ſelf</l>
                     <l>Aſtright fool-Mortals: If thou deſireſt</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Aphelia</hi>'s death, t'appeaſe thy troubled Soul,</l>
                     <l>Make ſome conſenting ſign and ſo depart,</l>
                     <l>Thy ſight afflicts my Soul.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Exit</hi> Landrey. <hi>Enter</hi> Queen.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
                     <p>How fares our Son?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clot.</speaker>
                     <p>Oh I am full of faintings, nothing but <hi>Aphelia?</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
                     <p>She muſt dye, you ſee it's requiſite.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clot.</speaker>
                     <p>Would he had askt my life firſt.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Eunuch.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
                     <p>Why ſhould you be ſo fond upon a Woman,</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clot.</speaker>
                     <p>Woman's the leaſt part in her, ſhe's all goddeſs.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
                     <l>'Twas your offer;</l>
                     <l>Remember there's no jeſting with the gods.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
                     <l>What might this mean? ha? where are my brains?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clot.</speaker>
                     <l>I had forgot my ſelf, your pardon Mother:</l>
                     <l>Bear her from me this Jewel, I eſteem</l>
                     <stage>gives her a Jewel.</stage>
                     <l>Equal with life, it was my Brothers Picture;</l>
                     <l>And with it, this, that ſhe prepare to dye</l>
                     <l>Tell her, and if you can be moved to ſorrow</l>
                     <l>Expreſs it in your tears, it is not I</l>
                     <l>Pronounce this fatal Sentence 'gainſt her life,</l>
                     <pb n="22" facs="tcp:57541:14"/>
                     <l> But the hid will, and Providence of Heaven;</l>
                     <l>Againſt the which to be offended, were</l>
                     <l>As impious as not obey. <hi>Caſtrato</hi> ſtay,</l>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>Exeunt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>nines manet Eunuch who profers to go out.</hi>
                     </stage>
                     <l>And with thy COuncel cure thy dying Prince,</l>
                     <l>Thou art my boſome, Eunuch, and to thee</l>
                     <l>I dare unclaſp my Soul: What's to be done,</l>
                     <l>This is a damned Spirit I have ſeen</l>
                     <l>And comes to work my Ruine.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
                     <p>What Spirit?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clot.</speaker>
                     <l>My Brothers Spirit in Arms, here it came forth,</l>
                     <l>Here, from my Mothers Chamber as I knockt.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
                     <p>Was it in Armour ſaid you? what in Armour?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clot.</speaker>
                     <l>Yes in the Armour he was us'd to wear</l>
                     <l>When we have run at Tilt, 'till our cleft Spears</l>
                     <l>Have with their ſplinters ſcar'd the Element.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
                     <l>That Armour as I well remember, I did leave</l>
                     <l>In the Queens Bed-Chamber, as yeſterday</l>
                     <l>After the Triumphs and the Turnements,</l>
                     <l>Having unbrac't the Prince: 'tis even ſo.</l>
                     <l>Why this is a ridiculous Paſſion.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clot.</speaker>
                     <p>My ſtate requires thy tears, and not thy mirth.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
                     <l>The Devil came from your Mothers Chamber Sir,</l>
                     <l>She has a Circle which can raiſe a Spirit,</l>
                     <l>A <hi>Mars</hi> in Armour too; ſhe is a <hi>Venus,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>And through your Licenſe <hi>Landrey</hi> is no Eunuch.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clot.</speaker>
                     <l>What killing ſenſe thou utterſt,</l>
                     <l>There's ſomething in it I would underſtand</l>
                     <l>And yet I dare not. <hi>Landrey!</hi> how know'ſt thou this?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
                     <l>Since I have gone ſo far I'le tell you.</l>
                     <l>I look'd in at the Key-hole, and I ſaw</l>
                     <l>Him in your Mothers Arms, as ſportingly</l>
                     <l>As e're I ſaw your Father.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clot.</speaker>
                     <l>Thou haſt ſhot Poyſon thro' me:</l>
                     <l>Falſe with <hi>Landrey</hi> her ſometime-Page!</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
                     <p>Even with the ſame.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clot.</speaker>
                     <l>It's not impoſſible,</l>
                     <l>My Mother always had a ſcanted fame,</l>
                     <stage>aſide.</stage>
                     <l>His thoughts to have been mine: I am diſtracted.</l>
                     <l>Was he the fearful Viſion that I ſaw?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
                     <p>Upon my life he was.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clot.</speaker>
                     <p>But wherefore would they have <hi>Aphelia</hi> dye?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
                     <l>There lies the Myſtery,</l>
                     <l>They fear you will accept her as your Queen,</l>
                     <l>And fruſtrate their intents, who but expect</l>
                     <pb n="23" facs="tcp:57541:14"/>
                     <l> Your hop'd for death, that they might ſo become</l>
                     <l>(What now you'd croſs) Lawfully Man and Wife</l>
                     <l>And Govern in your Seak.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clot.</speaker>
                     <l>This carries ſhew of truth, or is't a lye</l>
                     <l>Well ſhaddow'd by a Slave? I cannot tell;</l>
                     <l>My Mother certainly is not ſo bad,</l>
                     <l>It is a ſin to think it: Hence, avoid my ſight,</l>
                     <l>Thou ſower of debate, thy Seeds are ſtrow'd</l>
                     <l>On ſteril ground, and therefore ill beſtow'd.</l>
                     <stage>Exit.</stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
                     <l>Is't even ſo? work and about my brain</l>
                     <l>I'me loſt for ever if not cloſe again.</l>
                     <stage>Exit.</stage>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="scene">
                  <head>SCENE <hi>II.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Dumaine, Martel, Burbon, Lanoue.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lanoue.</speaker>
                     <l>Are all your Troops well furniſh'd gainſt reſiſtance?</l>
                     <l>Are your men bold and daring? reſolute</l>
                     <l>To run your hazzard? indifferent rich, not poor</l>
                     <l>That only fight for Bread? ſuch oft betrary</l>
                     <l>The ſinews of a well-knit Plot for gain,</l>
                     <l>When theſe as well fight to deſend as win.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Dum.</speaker>
                     <l>Noble <hi>Lanoue;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Mine know, nor fear, nor death; Souls of that fire</l>
                     <l>They'l catch the Bullet flying, ſcale a Wall</l>
                     <l>Battled with Enemy, ſtand Breaches, laugh</l>
                     <l>The Thunder of the Canon, call it Muſick</l>
                     <l>Fitter a Ladies Chamber then the Field;</l>
                     <l>When o're their heads the Element is ſcaled,</l>
                     <l>Darken'd with Darts, they'l ſight under the ſhade,</l>
                     <l>And ask no other roof to hide their heads in;</l>
                     <l>They fear not <hi>Jove,</hi> and had the Gyants been</l>
                     <l>But half ſo ſpirited they had dethron'd him.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lan.</speaker>
                     <l>They're Soldiers fit to ſack a Kingdom then,</l>
                     <l>And ſhare the ſpoils between them.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bur.</speaker>
                     <p>Were it come to that ſport once—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Burbone</hi> it muſt, or ſome of us muſt fall.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lan.</speaker>
                     <p>Where ſhall we firſt attempt?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Dum.</speaker>
                     <p>The Pallace.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Burb.</speaker>
                     <p>I ſay no, it's dangerous.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Dum.</speaker>
                     <p>It is the ſafeſt courſe.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <pb n="24" facs="tcp:57541:15"/>
                     <speaker>Mart.</speaker>
                     <p>Believe it not, for it is full of hazzard.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Dum.</speaker>
                     <p>So is the general enterprize in hand.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mart.</speaker>
                     <p>But this of certain ruine,</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lan.</speaker>
                     <l>Give us a reaſon why you would invade</l>
                     <l>The Pallace firſt, and we are ſatisfied.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Dum.</speaker>
                     <l>Now you ſpeak like your ſelf:</l>
                     <l>Then underſtand, <hi>Lamot</hi> lives ſtill at Court</l>
                     <l>Diſguis'd like a poor Chyrurgeon,</l>
                     <l>To whom the Prince being delievered</l>
                     <l>to be Embalm'd and Bowel'd, finding life</l>
                     <l>Yet in his Corps, which may he's very Skillfull;</l>
                     <l>Has balſom'd all his wounds and cur'd him.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lan.</speaker>
                     <p>And what of this? This makes againſt us quite.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Dum.</speaker>
                     <l>I did but even now receive this letter,</l>
                     <l>Which conſtancy affirms it from himſelf.</l>
                     <l>He ſays it is not known in Court, the Prince to live</l>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>gives</hi> Lan.</stage>
                     <l>For divers reaſons beſt known to themſelves,</l>
                     <l>And herein doth require of ſecreſy;</l>
                     <l>Therefore dear friend divulge it not.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lan.</speaker>
                     <l>He ſays the Princes ſuppoſed funeral</l>
                     <l>This day is ſolemnized with greateſt pomp,</l>
                     <l>And that <hi>Aphelia</hi> dyes a ſacrifice,</l>
                     <l>That hour he is buried, on his Herſe:</l>
                     <l>What if we made attempt to ſave the Virgin?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Dum.</speaker>
                     <l>That muſt not be, better ſhe fall alone</l>
                     <l>Then all of us together; and now beſt Friends,</l>
                     <l>Let's behave us bravely; it's no baſe act</l>
                     <l>We undertake, but our whole Countries freedom</l>
                     <l>From ſlavery and bondage, Men of worth ſtand bare</l>
                     <l>To Pages, and gilt butterflies, beſides the Queen</l>
                     <l>Will grave us all, rather then want ſport</l>
                     <l>In ſpilling Humane bloud; come let's withdraw,</l>
                     <l>And lay the Platform of this mighty work:</l>
                     <l>My Soul ſits ſmiling in me I Divine,</l>
                     <l>Though now it lowre we ſhall ſee Sun will ſhine.</l>
                     <stage>Drum.</stage>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="scene">
                  <head>SCENE <hi>III.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Clovis, <hi>and</hi> Lamot <hi>diſguis'd like a</hi> Chyrurgeon. <hi>Recorders.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clov.</speaker>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Strephon,</hi> for ſo thou nam'ſt thy ſelf, thou'ſt made</l>
                     <l>Thy Prince thy Subject, by this timely cure,</l>
                     <pb n="25" facs="tcp:57541:15"/>
                     <l> This is the hour I muſt be buried living,</l>
                     <l>And with me the Fair <hi>Aphelia, Strephon</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Is it ſo?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lamot.</speaker>
                     <l>Nay this the very Minute,</l>
                     <l>Hark, I hear them coming—</l>
                     <stage>a dead March within.</stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clov.</speaker>
                     <l>Lend me thy Cloak</l>
                     <l>Here we'le obſerve the Mourners.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Recorders. <hi>Enter</hi> King, Fredegond, <hi>and attendance, and</hi> Eunuch <hi>at one door in Mourning as after the C<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>p<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> of</hi> Clovis; <hi>at the other</hi> Aphelia <hi>led by two boys, a Headſman before as to Sacrifice, all in White, the Herſe is ſet down between both the Companies,</hi> Aphelia <hi>we pin<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> at one End, and the</hi> King <hi>at the other, who after a little pauſe speaks as followeth; after theſe Old</hi> Briſſac <hi>weeping.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clot.</speaker>
                     <l>Thou Royal load of Honour, burthen of grace,</l>
                     <l>Fitting an <hi>Atlas</hi> Shoulder, which he groans</l>
                     <l>More then the Spheres and Sweats thy weight not theirs;</l>
                     <l>Let me bedew thy Herſe with pious tears,</l>
                     <l>(Balm to thy wounds) repenting ones;</l>
                     <l>Behold this ſpotleſs ſacrifice, a virgin,</l>
                     <l>As pure in thought as veſture, an oblation</l>
                     <l>To ranſom <hi>Jove</hi> and Heaven had they been taken,</l>
                     <l>And ſo we yeild her up.</l>
                     <stage>gives her to the Headſman.</stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Briſ.</speaker>
                     <l>Oh my good Lord,</l>
                     <l>This is conſpiracy 'gainſt an old mans life,</l>
                     <l>Have you no other way to murther me</l>
                     <l>But to begin with Her? Why muſt ſhe dye?</l>
                     <l>Becauſe ſhe's fair? or that—</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clot.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Briſſac,</hi> peace:</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clov.</speaker>
                     <p>What Pagent's this?</p>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>the</hi> King <hi>takes the Sword from the Headſman.</hi>
                     </stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lam.</speaker>
                     <l>Contain your ſelf</l>
                     <l>You may prevent the danger when you pleaſe.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clot.</speaker>
                     <l>Behold the Conqueſt of thine eyes <hi>Aphelia,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>France</hi> at thy foot, tread on his Royalty,</l>
                     <l>Or if thy Nature knows not to forgive;</l>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>the</hi> King <hi>kneels and lays the Sword at</hi> Aphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lia's <hi>feet.</hi>
                     </stage>
                     <l>Which to believe were impious, take this Sword</l>
                     <l>Send me a willing, willing ſacrifice,</l>
                     <l>T'appeaſe the troubled ſpirit of this love.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
                     <p>O <hi>Eunuch</hi> that ſhe'd take him at his word.</p>
                     <stage>aſide.</stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clot.</speaker>
                     <l>I find <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> ſpeaking pitty in thine eyes,</l>
                     <l>Which thence will drop upon thy gentle tongue</l>
                     <l>And cry, In peace long live my Sovereign.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Aphe.</speaker>
                     <p>Long live <hi>Clotaire,</hi> long live my Sovereign.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <pb n="26" facs="tcp:57541:16"/>
                     <speaker>Clot.</speaker>
                     <l>The Motions of the Spheres move in that tongue:</l>
                     <l>Turn all your Sables into ſutes of Joy,</l>
                     <l>Your dirges into ſprightfull wedding airs:</l>
                     <l>Why looks our Court ſo ſad, is this a time</l>
                     <l>To anchor your aſpects unto the earth?</l>
                     <l>By my bleſt ſelf he's a traytor to the height</l>
                     <l>That does not ſtreight Salute her as his Queen.</l>
                     <stage>they ſting off their Mourn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Cloaks.</stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Om.</speaker>
                     <p>Long live <hi>Aphelia,</hi> Queen of <hi>France,</hi> and us.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>La.</speaker>
                     <p>Do you hear this? what are you Planet-ſtruck? <hi>Glovis,</hi> Prince, Monſieur.</p>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>the</hi> Cardinal <hi>contracts them.</hi>
                     </stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clot.</speaker>
                     <p>Cardinal—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lam.</speaker>
                     <l>Now, now, prevent them yet, are you a ſtone?</l>
                     <l>Have you a working Pulſe? O Statue-Prince</l>
                     <l>Thou art undone for ever.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clov.</speaker>
                     <l>Where am I?</l>
                     <l>Awake! for ever rather let me ſleep:</l>
                     <l>Is this a Funeral? oh that I were a Herſe,</l>
                     <stage>diſcloſes himſelf.</stage>
                     <l>And not the mock of what is Pageanted.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clot.</speaker>
                     <p>Amazement quite confounds us, <hi>Clovis</hi> alive!</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clov.</speaker>
                     <l>Oh that in nature I could find an art</l>
                     <l>Could teach me to forget, I ever lov'd</l>
                     <l>This, her great maſter-piece. Oh well-built frame</l>
                     <l>why do'ſt thou harbour ſuch unhallow'd gheſts</l>
                     <l>To houſe within thy boſom, Perjury?</l>
                     <l>If that our Vows are regiſtred in heaven</l>
                     <l>Why are they broke on earth? <hi>Aphelia</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>This was a haſty match, the ſubtle air</l>
                     <l>Has not yet cool'd the breath, with which thou ſwor'ſt</l>
                     <l>Thy ſelf into my ſoul; and on thy cheeks</l>
                     <l>The print and path-way of thoſe tears remain</l>
                     <l>That woo'd me to believe ſo: Fly me not,</l>
                     <l>I am no Spirit, touch my active pulſe</l>
                     <l>And thou ſhalt find it make ſuch harmony</l>
                     <l>As youth and health enjoy.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
                     <p>The Queen, ſhe faints.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clov.</speaker>
                     <l>Is there a god left ſo propitious</l>
                     <l>To rid me of theſe fears? ſtill lot her ſleep;</l>
                     <l>For if ſhe wake (O King) ſhe will appear</l>
                     <l>Too Monſtrous a ſpecter for frail Eyes</l>
                     <l>To ſee, and keep her Senſes.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lamot.</speaker>
                     <p>Are you Mad?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clov.</speaker>
                     <l>Nothing ſo happy, <hi>Strephon,</hi> I would I were.</l>
                     <l>In times Swift-progreſs, I deſpair the hour</l>
                     <l>That brings ſuch comfort with it; I ſhould then</l>
                     <pb n="27" facs="tcp:57541:16"/>
                     <l> Forget that ever ſhe was pleaſing to me,</l>
                     <l>I ſhould no more remember ſhe would ſit</l>
                     <l>And ſing mo into Dreams of Paradice,</l>
                     <l>Never more hang about her Ivory Neck</l>
                     <l>Believing ſuch a one <hi>Diana</hi> was;</l>
                     <l>Never more doat ſhe breaths <hi>Arabia,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Or Kiſs her Corral Lip into a paleneſs.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clot.</speaker>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Clovis</hi> what's paſt we are content to think</l>
                     <l>It was ſpoken by our Brother, and not our Subject,</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clov.</speaker>
                     <l>I had forgot my ſelf; yet well remember</l>
                     <l>Yon <hi>Gorgon</hi> has Transform'd me into Stone,</l>
                     <l>And ſince that time my Language has been harſh,</l>
                     <l>My words too heavy for my tongue, too earthly;</l>
                     <l>I was not horn ſo; Truſt me <hi>Aphelia</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Before I was poſſeſt with theſe black thoughts</l>
                     <l>I could ſit by thy ſide, and reſt my head</l>
                     <l>Upon the riſing pillows of thy Breaſt</l>
                     <l>Whoſe natural ſweetneſs would invite mine eyes</l>
                     <l>To ſink in pleaſing ſlumbers, wake and kiſs</l>
                     <l>The Roſe-bods that afforded me ſuch bliſs.</l>
                     <l>But thou art now a General Diſeaſe</l>
                     <l>That cateſt into my Marrow, turn'ſt my blood</l>
                     <l>And makeſt my Veins run Poyſon, that each ſenſe</l>
                     <l>Groans at the alteration. Am I the <hi>Monſieur?</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Does <hi>Clovis</hi> talk his ſorrows and not Act?</l>
                     <l>Oh man be womanized; wert thou not mine</l>
                     <l>How comes it thou art his?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clot.</speaker>
                     <l>You have done ill,</l>
                     <l>And muſt be taught ſo; you Capitulate</l>
                     <l>Not with your equal, <hi>Clovis</hi> ſhe's thy Queen.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clov.</speaker>
                     <l>Upon my Knees I do acknowledge her,</l>
                     <l>Queen of my thoughts, and my affections,</l>
                     <l>O pardon me if my ill tutored tongue</l>
                     <l>Has forfeited my Head; if not, behold</l>
                     <l>Before the Sacred Altar of your Feet</l>
                     <l>I lie a willing Sacrifice.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Aph.</speaker>
                     <l>Ariſe:</l>
                     <l>And henceforth <hi>C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>nis</hi> thus inſtruct thy Soul;</l>
                     <l>There he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> a depth in face, which earthly eyes</l>
                     <l>May faintly look into but cannot f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>thoſe</l>
                     <l>T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                           <desc>••••</desc>
                        </gap> had'ſt my Vow 'till death to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> thy Wiſe,</l>
                     <l>You <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </l>
                     <l>A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                           <desc>•••</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap> beſtowed.</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 line">
                           <desc>〈1 line〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </l>
                     <pb n="28" facs="tcp:57541:17"/>
                     <l> A long-farewell to Love; thus I do break</l>
                     <stage>breaks a Ring</stage>
                     <l>Your Pledge of broken faith. And with this Kiſs,</l>
                     <l>The laſt that ever <hi>Clovis</hi> muſt print there</l>
                     <l>Un-kiſs that Kiſs which ſeal'd it on thy Lips:</l>
                     <l>Ye Powers ye are unjuſt, for her wild breath</l>
                     <l>(That has the Sacred tye of Contract broken)</l>
                     <l>Is ſtill the ſame <hi>Arabia</hi> that it was.</l>
                     <l>Nay I have done; beware of Jelouſy;</l>
                     <l>I would not have you nouriſh jelous thoughts,</l>
                     <l>Tho' ſhe has broke her ſaith to me, to you</l>
                     <l>Againſt her Reputation, ſhe'l be true;</l>
                     <l>Farewell my firſt Love Loſt, I'le chooſe to have</l>
                     <l>No Wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>e till death ſhall wed me to my Grave,</l>
                     <l>Come <hi>Streph<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>n,</hi> come, and teach me how to dye,</l>
                     <l>That gav'ſt me Li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>e ſo unadviſedly.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Exeunt</hi> Clov. <hi>&amp;</hi> Lam.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clot.</speaker>
                     <l>'T was mine I ſent it to <hi>Aphelia;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>the King here beholds in</hi> Landreys <hi>Hat the J<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>wel he ſent by his Mother to</hi> Aphelia.</stage>
                     <l>Mother I've found your <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>inion; but no more,</l>
                     <l>The time's not ripe: ſomething I muſt do—</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
                     <l>Call back the Monſieur, let him not</l>
                     <l>Depart ſo full of grief.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clot.</speaker>
                     <l>Mother content your ſelf;</l>
                     <l>Let <hi>Clovis</hi> that way go, this way will we,</l>
                     <l>He's great with grief, we with felicity.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Exeunt omnes mauent</hi> Qu. <hi>&amp;</hi> Bunuch.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
                     <l>Miſchief grows lean <hi>Caſtrato,</hi> all our Plots</l>
                     <l>Turn head upon themſelves; my brain's grown weak</l>
                     <l>And in this Globe the Policy's not leſt</l>
                     <l>To kill a Worm unſeen; I am undone</l>
                     <l>And all my Plots diſcover'd:</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Eunuch.</speaker>
                     <l>This is Strange.</l>
                     <l>Some commick devil croſſeth our deſigns,</l>
                     <l>How elſe ſhould he revive? or you, prepar'd,</l>
                     <l>Nay, in the arms of <hi>Landrey,</hi> when deſire</l>
                     <l>Had made you all a <hi>Venus,</hi> meet events</l>
                     <l>So barren in their expectations?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
                     <l>There lies the grief <hi>Caſtrato;</hi> had the Court</l>
                     <l>(So I had quencht theſe burning flames)</l>
                     <l>Been buried in her cinders I had not car<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>d.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
                     <l>But yet <hi>Landreys</hi> eſcape does qualify</l>
                     <l>The non-performance.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
                     <l>That ſits ſmiling here:</l>
                     <l>It ſet my brains upon the ten<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ors, Eunuch,</l>
                     <l>Was't not a rare device?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
                     <l>And was not I</l>
                     <l>As fortunate to leave that Armour there?</l>
                     <pb n="29" facs="tcp:57541:17"/>
                     <l> But now what's to be done?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
                     <l>My dull <hi>Aetiope</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>I will inſtruct thy blackneſs, learn to know</l>
                     <l>My reputation's ſickned, and my fame</l>
                     <l>Is look'd into with narrow eyes at Court,</l>
                     <l>Therefore it's thus decreed: I will remove</l>
                     <l>And ſequeſter my ſelf from Company.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
                     <p>Good.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
                     <l>Thou know'ſt where <hi>Childrick</hi> kept his Concubine</l>
                     <l>To none diſcover'd but thy ſelf and me,</l>
                     <l>For which they are no more.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
                     <p>Right.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
                     <l>There will I</l>
                     <l>And my <hi>Landrey</hi> ſecurely ſpend our time;</l>
                     <l>Revell, embrace, and what not my Eunuch?</l>
                     <l>The Cave that leads unto the Poſtern-Gate</l>
                     <l>Which <hi>Childrick</hi> made will give him entrance</l>
                     <l>No eye acquainted; being thus retired</l>
                     <l>What Luſt inſlam'd muſt be by Luſt un-ſired.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
                     <p>Excellent Miſtreſs I applaud your brain.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
                     <l>I will away to night, I cannot brook</l>
                     <l>Theſe loathed Nuptials, they have undone</l>
                     <l>My hopes on earth for ever; therefore away,</l>
                     <l>Acquaint <hi>Landrey</hi> with theſe deſigns.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
                     <p>What elſe?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
                     <l>If by the engino of thy ſtronger brain</l>
                     <l>Thou could'ſt remove—</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Aphelia,</hi> or the King,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Monſieur</hi> or all, is it not ſo my Queen?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
                     <l>Thou haſt a brain which doth ingender thoughts</l>
                     <l>As regal as our own; which does beget</l>
                     <l>A race of rare events; what pity 'tis</l>
                     <l>Thy body ſhould be ſterril, ſith thy mind</l>
                     <l>Is of ſo pregnant and a fruitfull kind:</l>
                     <l>Farewell remember me.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Exit.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
                     <l>Remember you, you ſhall be thought on, ſear it not.</l>
                     <l>And now bethink thee <hi>Eunuch,</hi> all thy Flots</l>
                     <l>Find fruit leſs goodneſs, only in the King:</l>
                     <l>His Worſhip walk'd into the other World</l>
                     <l>Like a tame Sucking-Child that dy'd of the Pip.</l>
                     <l>The trouble is behind, my hare extends</l>
                     <l>To the whole Family, I muſt root them up;</l>
                     <l>And Beldam firſt with you: But how? but how?</l>
                     <l>It in her proud deſires, I prevent</l>
                     <pb n="30" facs="tcp:57541:18"/>
                     <l> Her Luſt this Second time, before the Third</l>
                     <l>She may repent and ſave her loathed Soul,</l>
                     <l>Which my Revenge would Damn; yet were ſhe croſt</l>
                     <l>Her Luſt, being now at full flood within her,</l>
                     <l>And no way left to quench her burning flames,</l>
                     <l>Her dryer Bones would make a Bonefire</l>
                     <l>Fit for the Devil to warm his hands by.</l>
                     <l>Ha! Shall it be thus? No it muſt not be;</l>
                     <l>Nor muſt the high and mighty Queen <hi>Aphelia</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>This Night Enjoy her Bridegroom, I muſt ſet</l>
                     <l>Some Miſchief inſtantly on foot to croſs it,</l>
                     <l>If I miſcarry in't, Story ſhall tell</l>
                     <l>I did attempt it bravely tho' I fell.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Offers to go off, &amp; met with the</hi> M. <hi>&amp;</hi> La.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clov.</speaker>
                     <l>Diſwade me not <hi>Caſtrato!</hi> I have ſought thee</l>
                     <l>Through every angle of this ſpatious Court,</l>
                     <l>I've bus'neſs to impart.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
                     <p>And ſo have I.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clov.</speaker>
                     <l>Mine are of Honourable conſequence</l>
                     <l>And do require thine aid.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
                     <p>So does mine yours.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clov.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Aphelia</hi> is—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
                     <l>Your Brother's Wife, and you</l>
                     <l>Would fain injoy her too? Why ſir you may,</l>
                     <l>But time muſt work her.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clov.</speaker>
                     <l>Eunuch thou art wide,</l>
                     <l>Thoſe vanities of Love are quite Extinct,</l>
                     <l>Revenge does ſwell the Monſieur, and his thoughts</l>
                     <l>Which burns within him muſt be quencht with blood,</l>
                     <l>Seeſt thou this Letter, 'tis a ſcript I ſeign'd,</l>
                     <stage>ſhews him a Letter.</stage>
                     <l>For I can Counterſeit <hi>Aphelia's</hi> hand,</l>
                     <l>The King has baniſht <hi>Landrey</hi> from the Court</l>
                     <l>Becauſe he wore the Jewel which he ſent</l>
                     <l>To his <hi>Aphelia,</hi> light ſuſpicious</l>
                     <l>But this ſhall aggrevate: find thou the King,</l>
                     <l>Shew him this note, it doth expreſs great Love</l>
                     <l>To <hi>Landrey</hi> from <hi>Aphelia</hi> and withall</l>
                     <l>It mentioneth the Jewel as a gift</l>
                     <l>To gratify her ſervant, this to the reſt</l>
                     <l>Of poyſon he has ſuckt already in</l>
                     <l>Shall ſo inflame him, that the Court ſhall burn</l>
                     <l>Too Hot for his <hi>Aphelia</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
                     <l>Think it done:</l>
                     <l>But now your aid, ſince that your mind is bent</l>
                     <l>On Honourable deeds, here's one will try you.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <pb n="31" facs="tcp:57541:18"/>
                     <speaker>Clov.</speaker>
                     <l>What is it Eunuch?</l>
                     <l>If that is bare an honourable Name;</l>
                     <l>Tho' death ſtood gaping wide to ſwallow me</l>
                     <l>I will not ſhrink nor fear.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
                     <l>Noble: Hear't then.</l>
                     <l>Your mother's looſe, and this night renders up</l>
                     <l>Her body unto luſt if not prevented,</l>
                     <l>I can direct you how, and where, with whom,</l>
                     <l>If you'l be tame, be tame, diſhonou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> blots</l>
                     <l>Your Princely Parentage.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clov.</speaker>
                     <l>My ſoul finds the Man</l>
                     <l>Is't not <hi>Landrey?</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
                     <p>The ſame.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clov.</speaker>
                     <l>I'le tear him all to pieces,</l>
                     <l>Whore my mother? Eunuch lead the way,</l>
                     <l>In what thou ſhalt preſcribe, we will obey.</l>
                     <stage>Exeunt Omnes</stage>
                  </sp>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="act">
               <head>ACT <hi>IV</hi>
               </head>
               <div n="1" type="scene">
                  <head>SCENE <hi>I.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>A Bed. Enter</hi> Clotaire <hi>Solus.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clot.</speaker>
                     <l>WHat vulture gripes me here: ha, what art thou?</l>
                     <l>If thou be'ſt jelouſy, mount and be gone;</l>
                     <l>Fly to the vulgar boſome, whoſe cheap thoughts,</l>
                     <l>Deſpair their own performance; in a King</l>
                     <l>Thou ſhew'ſt a Nature retrograde to Honour.</l>
                     <l>Suppoſe ſhe gave the jewel, muſt in follow</l>
                     <l>She therefore is diſloyal, poor conſequence</l>
                     <l>A bubble for a boy to play withal.</l>
                     <l>I am reſolv'd; Heark I hear her coming:</l>
                     <l>O <hi>Juno</hi> what a gate and look is there?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Soft Muſick. Enter</hi> Aphelia, Iſabel, Julia, <hi>with Tapers as having</hi> Aphelia <hi>to Bed.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Aph.</speaker>
                     <l>Mock me not Ladies with this Ceremony,</l>
                     <l>For I am ſitter to attend on you,</l>
                     <l>I am become a Servant and a Slave</l>
                     <l>To every moody Paſſion of my Lord:</l>
                     <l>Pray leave me, all that's behind</l>
                     <l>I can perform my ſelf.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <pb n="32" facs="tcp:57541:19"/>
                     <speaker>Iſa.</speaker>
                     <p>Great Queen of <hi>France.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Aph.</speaker>
                     <l>That name of Queen ſounds ſtrangely in mine ears,</l>
                     <l>It's like a Language that I once could ſpeak,</l>
                     <l>But now have quite forgot, call not me Queen;</l>
                     <l>All Gilded Royalties I'le quite renounce,</l>
                     <l>And all my ſtudy ſhall be how to dye:</l>
                     <l>Empreſs of woe, and Queen fo Miſery.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Jul.</speaker>
                     <l>You muſt not weigh theſe things ſo deep,</l>
                     <l>Your Lord is of an honourable ſpirit,</l>
                     <l>And you will ſee how calm he will return,</l>
                     <l>Bleſſing your bridal b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>d with fruitfull Iſſue.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Aph.</speaker>
                     <l>No, No.</l>
                     <l>The Saffron-colour'd <hi>Hymen</hi> frowns upon me:</l>
                     <l>Theſe Tapers too were lighted at a Pike,</l>
                     <l>As <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>it attendants on the Grave, not Bed.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Juno</hi> denye; her preſence at this match</l>
                     <l>And all the ill preſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>gi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>g Birds of Night</l>
                     <l>Sing ſatal Req<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>iems for a bridal ſong</l>
                     <l>Oh Ladies, is not this ominous?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clot.</speaker>
                     <l>Yes my <hi>Aphelia</hi> if that rugged fate</l>
                     <l>Lye in a kiſs then it is ominous,</l>
                     <l>Her kiſſes melt upon my lip: if ſin</l>
                     <l>Have ſo much heaven in it, I'le be a ſinner.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Aph.</speaker>
                     <l>I hope your ſears are ſatisfy'd now,</l>
                     <l>You bare a brow ſo pleaſant.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clot.</speaker>
                     <l>What pritty foolery is this <hi>Aphelia?</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>I am not jelous, for by all that's good,</l>
                     <l>I cannot think thee evil; go be gone</l>
                     <stage>Ex. manet Clot.</stage>
                     <l>Unharneſs your Lady for theſe warrs,</l>
                     <l>We're of the Camills and ſight naked.</l>
                     <l>Ye powers that favour lovers, infuſe apt Strength,</l>
                     <l>Though every Nerve and Sinew of this frame</l>
                     <l>Make me all pleaſure; and unto the Bride,</l>
                     <l>Add every vein a <hi>Venus;</hi> guide me light,</l>
                     <l>Where in one Bed lyes all the Worlds delight.</l>
                     <l>What knockings this? <hi>Caſtrato,</hi> what's the news?</l>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>knocking with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, Enter</hi> Eun.</stage>
                     <l>Deliver Briefly, for I am in haſt.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
                     <l>Not yet in Bed? oh happy, happy minute:</l>
                     <l>Untill this hour I ne're was fortunate,</l>
                     <l>I have preſerved my King, my Prince, my Patron,</l>
                     <l>From the looſe ardor of a Strumpets Bed.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clot.</speaker>
                     <p>What's this?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
                     <l>I deal not now on doubts; your wiſe is looſe</l>
                     <l>Diſhoneſt as the Suburbs, I am loth</l>
                     <pb n="33" facs="tcp:57541:19"/>
                     <l> To nominate her Whore tho' it be true.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clot.</speaker>
                     <p>True!—</p>
                     <stage>amazedly.</stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
                     <l>Leave this lethargiz'd paſſion, which benumbs</l>
                     <l>Your nobler nature; turn your eyes on theſe;</l>
                     <stage>gives him the Letter.</stage>
                     <l>Whoſe Character is this?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clot.</speaker>
                     <l>Ha! let me ſee:</l>
                     <l>This is <hi>Aphelia's</hi> hand, the very ſame</l>
                     <l>Which I have often ſeen <hi>Clovis</hi> peruſe</l>
                     <l>In his Loves amorous purſuit.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
                     <p>Real the Contents.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clot.</speaker>
                     <l>A Letter that ſhe loves <hi>Landrey,</hi> with thanks</l>
                     <l>For his ſo often viſits; which ſhe repays</l>
                     <l>With the rich Jewel ſent her by the King,</l>
                     <l>Wiſhing a perpetuity of embracements;</l>
                     <l>Ten thouſand Ravens croak in this black paper,</l>
                     <l>How came you by it?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
                     <l>I ſaw it drop from <hi>Landrey,</hi> but ne're thought</l>
                     <l>'Fore I perus'd it, what it did contain;</l>
                     <l>Which finding, in my duty I was bound</l>
                     <l>To ſave my Prince from ruine.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clot.</speaker>
                     <l>Follow me</l>
                     <l>Black vengeance ſteel my heart with cruelty.</l>
                     <stage>Exit.</stage>
                     <l>I'le take her ſleeping thus; it cannot be,</l>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>a Bed thruſt forth with</hi> Aphelia <hi>in it, Enter</hi> Clot. <hi>again and the</hi> Eunuch.</stage>
                     <l>Do but behold her face, and thou ſhalt read</l>
                     <l>What we call virtue there and modeſty;</l>
                     <l>Here is a look would perſuade cruelty</l>
                     <l>To ſigh and ſhed a tear, bribe <hi>Nemeſis</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>To knot her Steely Scourge with plumie down,</l>
                     <l>And <hi>Jove</hi> himſelf to call her vice a virtue.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
                     <l>A book of Devils may have the cover gilt,</l>
                     <l>Treaſon lies cabben'd in the ſmootheſt brow,</l>
                     <l>The Devil can aſſume an Angels form,</l>
                     <l>Your Wife is fair, but fair to do you harm.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clot.</speaker>
                     <p>Peace Villain, thou that infects all peace.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
                     <l>Why are you thus diſtemper'd? let not truth</l>
                     <l>Make you ſo wild a Tempeſt; were it falſe,</l>
                     <l>Or that I ſhought the ruine of your houſe</l>
                     <l>Your youth and honour, then it were a time</l>
                     <l>To ſwell beyond all charming down:</l>
                     <l>But being truth!</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clot.</speaker>
                     <l>Hence dog, avoid my ſight,</l>
                     <l>Fly where the under-world, ill vers'd in kindred,</l>
                     <l>Promiſcuouſly combine without diſtinction,</l>
                     <l>Where every man is every womans husband,</l>
                     <pb n="34" facs="tcp:57541:20"/>
                     <l> Or where it's thought a curteſy to have,</l>
                     <l>A fellow-ſharer in the marriage-bed:</l>
                     <l>Theſe were a People that might bare with thee</l>
                     <l>And ſit for thee to dwell with; hence, away,</l>
                     <l>And if thou lov'ſt thy life acquaint thy feet</l>
                     <l>With ſuch by paths that we may never meet.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Exit.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
                     <l>This Prince is of a nature milde and gentle,</l>
                     <l>His mother's milk's too fluent in his eyes,</l>
                     <l>And much I fear his reſolution;</l>
                     <l>Yet I will work him forward; ſhe awakes;</l>
                     <l>I'le after him and bring him back, if then</l>
                     <l>She ſcape his rage, Hell has no power with men.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Exit.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Aph.</speaker>
                     <l>Oh, oh, oh, help, help, my Lord, my Lord, my Father,</l>
                     <l>Oh my Lord.</l>
                     <l>Bleſs me Divinity, 'twas but a Dream;</l>
                     <l>Ha! the light gone, who waits there, <hi>Iſabel, Julia, Iſabel.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>Enter</hi> Iſabel.</stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iſab.</speaker>
                     <l>That was my Ladies voice; calls ſhe for help?</l>
                     <l>I cannot blame her, were I in her place</l>
                     <l>I ſhould do ſo my ſelf; the Prince looks like a bungler.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Aph.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Iſabel.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iſab.</speaker>
                     <p>Did you call Madam?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Aph.</speaker>
                     <p>Saw'ſt thou nothing <hi>Iſabel?</hi> where is my Lord?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iſab.</speaker>
                     <l>Is he abſent? I cannot blame her then to call for help;</l>
                     <l>I ſhould do't my ſelf; ſo near a good turn, and delay'd,</l>
                     <l>O it would mad me; a Prince, a Puppet would have</l>
                     <l>Been more manly; How do you Madam?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Aph.</speaker>
                     <p>All ſtands not well;</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iſab.</speaker>
                     <p>I believe that faithfully.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Aph.</speaker>
                     <l>O Girl, I've paſt the diſmal'ſt part of night</l>
                     <l>That ever made ſoft fancy fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>l.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iſab.</speaker>
                     <p>If all Brides ſhould be ſo ſool'd, I'de forſwear Marriage.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Aph.</speaker>
                     <l>Methought I ſaw my Father in a Vault,</l>
                     <l>His ſilver hair made crimſon by his bloud,</l>
                     <l>My Brother at his Herſe upon his knees</l>
                     <l>Taking a ſolemn Oath for his revenge,</l>
                     <l>Yet all this while ſo fancy fool'd my ſenſe</l>
                     <l>Methought that I was here, when on the inſtant</l>
                     <l>My Lord in preparation for my bed,</l>
                     <l>Was by an ugly Fiend raviſht from hence</l>
                     <l>And hurried to deſtruction, here I waked,</l>
                     <l>And truſt me <hi>Iſabel,</hi> I ſcarce believe</l>
                     <l>But what I ſaw was real. Heard'ſt thou nothing?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iſab.</speaker>
                     <l>I heard diſcourſe of People in your chamber</l>
                     <pb n="35" facs="tcp:57541:20"/>
                     <l> Not half an hour ſince: but they went forth</l>
                     <l>And to my ſeeming full of diſcontent,</l>
                     <l>But know not who they were.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Aph.</speaker>
                     <l>Oh it is true, help me <hi>Iſabel,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>I'le to my Fathers, my Prophetique ſoul</l>
                     <l>Sits like a Mine of Lead within me,</l>
                     <l>Come Girl.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iſab.</speaker>
                     <l>This ſad fight</l>
                     <l>Beſits a funeral, not a bridal night.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="scene">
                  <head>SCENE. <hi>II.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Clotaire <hi>and the</hi> Eunuch.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clot.</speaker>
                     <l>Eunuch I'me reſolved, I will be cruel</l>
                     <l>Since ſhe's deſil'd, and like a Chryſtal Well</l>
                     <l>That has her ſpring poyſoned by the enemy,</l>
                     <l>Of which it's death for the beſieg'd to taſte,</l>
                     <l>Such are adulterate waters. <hi>Caſtrato</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>What read'ſt thou in our brow?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
                     <p>A fooliſh grudging of the mother ſtill.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clot.</speaker>
                     <l>A ſettled reſolution my black Saint</l>
                     <l>Not to be alter'd by the brackiſh tears</l>
                     <l>Which flow in pregnant eyes of eaſy woman,</l>
                     <l>My honour calls for vengeance, and I'le do;</l>
                     <stage>looks on the Bed.</stage>
                     <l>Ha, how! ſhe's gone, and I have loſt mine anger too.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
                     <l>But whither is ſhe gone, to ſome new Groom,</l>
                     <l>Who being fool'd in expectation</l>
                     <l>Will make thee Cuckold on thy wedding night.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clot.</speaker>
                     <l>Thou haſt awaked me, I'le know where ſhe is;</l>
                     <l>Hell nor her darker deeds ſhall hide her from me:</l>
                     <l>Who waites? <hi>La-key.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>La.</speaker>
                     <p>My Lord.</p>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>Enter</hi> La-key.</stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clot.</speaker>
                     <p>Where is thy Lady? where is <hi>Aphelia?</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>La.</speaker>
                     <p>She's even now gone forth.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clot.</speaker>
                     <p>Forth! with whom?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>La.</speaker>
                     <l>There was one with her, but whether man or woman</l>
                     <l>I am uncertain; but ſure it was a man,</l>
                     <l>ſhe would not dare to venture out ſo late elſe.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Exit</hi> La-key.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clot.</speaker>
                     <l>Get to thy reſt</l>
                     <l>I'le take thy word Eunuch for the Kingdoms wealth.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <pb n="36" facs="tcp:57541:21"/>
                     <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
                     <l>Oh d'ye begin to credit now,</l>
                     <l>Now when perhaps it is too late.</l>
                     <l>This comes of patience.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clot.</speaker>
                     <l>Turn patience into fury, love to hate;</l>
                     <l>My ſofter temper to a heart of Steel;</l>
                     <l>Reſpect to Wedlock and the Sacred Vow</l>
                     <l>Made 'fore the Holy Alter to the Prieſt,</l>
                     <l>Thus I do fling ye off; Revenge ſhall move</l>
                     <l>About our Bridal-bed inſtead of Love.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Exeunt</stage>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="scene">
                  <head>SCENE <hi>III.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Clovis, Strephon, <hi>and the Watch.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clov.</speaker>
                     <p>Upon your lives let no man paſs that way.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Watch.</speaker>
                     <p>We ſhall obey in all.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clov.</speaker>
                     <l>If he reſiſt or offer violence</l>
                     <l>In his eſcape, knock out his brains.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Watch.</speaker>
                     <p>We'le do our beſt my Lord.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clov.</speaker>
                     <l>There's your reward, be carefull and be gone.</l>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>Ex.</hi> Watch.</stage>
                     <l>You ſhall poſſeſs the Cave: my ſelf will in</l>
                     <l>And viſit theſe night-revellers, ſuch ſport</l>
                     <l>I will adminiſter, ſhall make them dance</l>
                     <l>Lauolto's in the air; this ſhall Fiddle to them:</l>
                     <l>Have you the Habit <hi>Strephon?</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lam.</speaker>
                     <l>With theſe hands I did diſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>robe the Statue of your Father.</l>
                     <l>And they are ready.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clov.</speaker>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Landrey,</hi> bloud does ſwell</l>
                     <l>The Monſieur's thoughts, to ſend thy ſoul to Hell.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="scene">
                  <head>SCENE <hi>IV.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Landrey ſolus. <hi>Muſique above plays.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lan.</speaker>
                     <l>The air's perfum'd, each room thro' which I walk</l>
                     <l>Baqu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>s the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>s, courts the appetite</l>
                     <stage>Hole open.</stage>
                     <l>O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> every la<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>y <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>hat makes up man</l>
                     <l>To complement <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> into Paradiſe:</l>
                     <l>If then Elyſiun<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>'s h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>e, where are thoſe ſhades,</l>
                     <pb n="37" facs="tcp:57541:21"/>
                     <l> Thoſe bleſſed apparitions Poets feign?</l>
                     <l>Appear my goddeſs and out-ſing the Poets.</l>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>Enter</hi> Fredegonde.</stage>
                     <l>Reality of fancy, that exelleſt</l>
                     <l>The faint expreſſion of a lazy tongue</l>
                     <l>Whoſe roof is hous'd with fleſh, to tell thy worth,</l>
                     <l>Tongues tipt with Immortality would faint in't.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
                     <l>Excellent ſervant, what Houſe do you write to?</l>
                     <l>Poet and Actor both! why this ſudden gaze?</l>
                     <stage>he looks admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ringly on her.</stage>
                     <l>Your caſes are too narrow for your eyes,</l>
                     <l>Pray keep your optiques Sir, for <hi>Venus</hi> ſervice.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lan.</speaker>
                     <l>No,</l>
                     <l>I'le play the Prodigal with my precious ſight,</l>
                     <l>And ſpend all on you; to view your ſecond</l>
                     <l>Were ſuch a happineſs, after tho which,</l>
                     <l>It were a ſin to ſee more.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
                     <l>Bleſs me <hi>Rablais!</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>And all ye foſter fancies of the <hi>French,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>What ails the man! my <hi>Landrey-Laureat?</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lan.</speaker>
                     <l>It is my Queen that's <hi>Laureat,</hi> whoſe bleſt ſight</l>
                     <l>Creates a Poet; this divine feature</l>
                     <l>Heaven only fram'd to make men ingenuous.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
                     <l>Is this <hi>Extempore?</hi> or have you hired</l>
                     <l>Some Hackney-Muſe acquainted with the road</l>
                     <l>Of vulgar exorciſms, to charm ſweet Beauties?</l>
                     <l>Take up at this ſpeed, elſe your Muſe will founder.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lan.</speaker>
                     <l>Founder and have her foundreſs by! with patience</l>
                     <l>Hear but theſe poor expreſſion of your worth,</l>
                     <l>Which faintly Paint forth your perfections,</l>
                     <l>And you ſhall bleſs my Muſe.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
                     <l>We'le hear your Jigg,</l>
                     <l>How is your Ballad Titled? come pronounce.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lan.</speaker>
                     <l>From head to foot my Miſtreſs been</l>
                     <stage>Lan. <hi>rea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>,</hi>
                     </stage>
                     <l>Far excelling beauties Queen.</l>
                     <l>Had <hi>Jaſon</hi> but beheld her hair,</l>
                     <l>The Golden-Fleece had ne're ſeem'd fair.</l>
                     <l>Thoſe Stars (which Mortals ſuppoſe eyes),</l>
                     <l>Were aſcendant in the Skies:</l>
                     <l>When it fell to <hi>Venus</hi> lot</l>
                     <l>That little <hi>Cupid</hi> was begot.</l>
                     <l>Her tongue, (in which the Spheres do move</l>
                     <l>Organ of divineſt Love)</l>
                     <l>Was by <hi>Apollo</hi> fram'd, that he</l>
                     <l>From: hence might learn more harmony.</l>
                     <l>Who notes her teeth, and lips, diſcoloſes</l>
                     <pb n="38" facs="tcp:57541:22"/>
                     <l> Walls of Pearl, and Gates of Roſes,</l>
                     <l>Two-leaved-doors that lead the way</l>
                     <l>Through her breath t'<hi>Arabia;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>To which would <hi>Cupid</hi> grant that bliſs</l>
                     <l>I'de go a Pilgrimage to kiſs</l>
                     <l>Thoſe hills of Snow which on her breaſt</l>
                     <l>Riſe ſwelling with a double Creſt.</l>
                     <l>Mate <hi>Parnaſſus</hi> mountain, whence,</l>
                     <l>The Muſes ſuck their Eloquence.</l>
                     <l>Thoſe Parts which we will not diſcover,</l>
                     <l>He'l imagine that's a Lover.</l>
                     <l>Like <hi>Juno</hi> ſhe does go,</l>
                     <l>Like <hi>Pailas</hi> talk, and ſow,</l>
                     <l>Like <hi>Venus</hi> in her bliſs,</l>
                     <l>Each kiſs a <hi>Cupid</hi> is.</l>
                     <l>And her hands are as White as ſnow.</l>
                     <l>From head to foot <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
                     <l>Leave theſe aerial viands, taſt of what</l>
                     <l>Is here ſubſtantial; How like you the fruit?</l>
                     <stage>kiſſes her.</stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Land.</speaker>
                     <p>Let me for ever dwell upon theſe lips;</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
                     <l>You are too greedy of thoſe rarities;</l>
                     <l>And muſt be dieted, leſt ſurfeting,</l>
                     <l>Your Appetite ſhould ſicken and ſo dye.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lan.</speaker>
                     <l>Dye on your Lips, oh death-bed for a <hi>Jove</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Whoſe buried here his grave's immortal Love.</l>
                     <l>Here will I dwell and know not age nor ſorrow.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
                     <p>Yet <hi>Childrick</hi> knew them both.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lan.</speaker>
                     <l>A Froſty Prince</l>
                     <l>Begot on <hi>January</hi> by a Dutchman,</l>
                     <l>And worthy of thoſe flames he now indures.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
                     <p>What noiſe is this? guard me divinity.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Clov. <hi>from under the Stage in the old Kings habit,</hi> Land. <hi>flys off, the</hi> Qu. <hi>ſwoons: he flings <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ffkis habit &amp; holds her up.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clov.</speaker>
                     <l>What has my raſhneſs done! ſhe's my mother</l>
                     <l>My conſcience tells me I was much too blame</l>
                     <l>Thus to delude her ſenſes; ſhe returns.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
                     <l>Oh <hi>Childrick</hi> I confeſs 'twas I that kil'd thee,</l>
                     <l>Theſe hands adminiſtred that fatal dram</l>
                     <l>Which ſet thy ſoud on wing.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clov.</speaker>
                     <p>What do I hear?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
                     <l>Oh do not ſnatch my ſoul from out the world</l>
                     <l>Till I have bath'd it in repenting tears</l>
                     <l>And made it fit for Heaven.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clov.</speaker>
                     <l>She faints again.</l>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>Enter</hi> Strephon <hi>at the hole.</hi>
                     </stage>
                     <l>O Welcome <hi>Strephon,</hi> lend thy gentle hand</l>
                     <l>Which Maſter's Nature, and does life reſtore;</l>
                     <pb n="39" facs="tcp:57541:22"/>
                     <l> Beyond the art of <hi>Eſculapius,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Apply thy gentleſt medicines.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lam.</speaker>
                     <p>Let us withdraw, my life Sir anſwer hers if ſhe miſcarry.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Exeunt omnes.</stage>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="scene">
                  <head>SCENE <hi>V.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter the</hi> Watch.</stage>
                  <p n="1">1. Stand cloſe, ſtand cloſe, I heard a kind of buſsling e're while.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Buſsling, and they come this way here's that ſhall buſsle them.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Peace, peace; he's drunk and will betray us all.</p>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Lan.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lan.</speaker>
                     <l>I am betray'd, the Monſieur ſeeks my life,</l>
                     <l>All ways againſt my eſcape are ſortify'd.</l>
                     <l>Oh cruel Fortune, Bawd to time and Fate</l>
                     <l>That ſootheſt us up to make us ruinate.</l>
                     <l>Ha, what is here? great goddeſs pardon me,</l>
                     <stage>he finds the habie and puts it on.</stage>
                     <l>I have offended 'gainſt thy deity.</l>
                     <l>This ſhall delude the Watch; thrice bleſſed hap</l>
                     <l>That thus delivereſt whom they would intrap.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>2.</speaker>
                     <l>I will no ſtand, or I cannot ſtand, I ſay</l>
                     <stage>they pull the drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken Watchman to be quiet.</stage>
                     <l>I ſee a voice, d'<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>e think I'me drunk, what's</l>
                     <l>That horrid ſmell, what's that?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>1.3.</speaker>
                     <p>Bleſs us oh bleſs; diabolo, diabolo, diabolo.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>2.</speaker>
                     <l>The devil, what devil care I; keep off devil,</l>
                     <l>I ſay keep off; I do not fear thee: are you ſneaking</l>
                     <l>Back, you cowardly rogue d'ye budge; I hate a cowardly</l>
                     <l>Devil as I hate a drunkard, take you that.</l>
                     <stage>knooks him down.</stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lan.</speaker>
                     <p>Oh, oh, oh.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>2.</speaker>
                     <l>Oh, oh; I'le warrant you I'le make you cry oh: what a devil</l>
                     <l>Made you in my way: I will now ſee what money you carry</l>
                     <l>About you: men ſay the Prince of darkneſs is a Gentleman;</l>
                     <l>By'r Lady he ha good cloaths on, but yet for all that</l>
                     <l>He may have no money.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Clovis, Strephon, <hi>and the</hi> Queen. Strephon <hi>with his falſe Beard off.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
                     <l>I know not where he is, or if I did,</l>
                     <l>Before I'de yield him up to thy revenge</l>
                     <l>I'de dye ten thouſand deaths.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <pb n="40" facs="tcp:57541:23"/>
                     <speaker>Clov.</speaker>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Strephon, Strephon,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>For ſo I ſtill muſt call thee, thou haſt ſeen,</l>
                     <l>And heard thoſe things delivered, that do ſplie</l>
                     <l>My heart in ſunder, yet amongſt theſe griefs</l>
                     <l>Which ſit like Mines of Lead upon my ſoul</l>
                     <l>There is one corner of my heart that joys</l>
                     <l>Thy innocent bloud has ſcaped butchery.</l>
                     <l>Thou glorious light that in thine natural orb</l>
                     <l>Did'ſt comfortably ſhine upon this Kingdom,</l>
                     <l>How is thy worth eclypſed? what a dull darkneſs</l>
                     <l>Hangs about thy ſame? in all this piece</l>
                     <l>To every limb whereof I once paid duty,</l>
                     <l>I know not where to find my Mother.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
                     <p>The devil and diſobedience blinds your eyes.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clov.</speaker>
                     <l>Oh that I had no eyes, ſo you no ſhame:</l>
                     <l>Murther your Husband to arrive at Luſt,</l>
                     <l>And then to lay the guilt on innocents:</l>
                     <l>Bluſh, bluſh thou worſe then Woman.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
                     <p>Ha, ha, ha.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clov.</speaker>
                     <l>Hold my heart,</l>
                     <l>You're impudent in ſin, has your proud Page</l>
                     <l>Made you thus valiant? tell me where he is,</l>
                     <l>For if you dally with me, know this hand</l>
                     <l>Shall pull him from thy heart tho' cabbin'd there.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
                     <l>How dar'ſt thou cloath thy ſpeech in ſuch a phraſe</l>
                     <l>To me thy natural Mother?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clov.</speaker>
                     <l>My Mother!</l>
                     <l>Adulterate woman, ſhame of Royalty</l>
                     <l>I bluſh to call thee Mother: thy foul Luſts</l>
                     <l>Have taught me words of that harſh conſequence</l>
                     <l>That ſtigmatize obedience, and do brand</l>
                     <l>With miſ becoming accents filial duty.</l>
                     <l>Deliver quickly where this Leacher is,</l>
                     <l>Here hous'd he muſt be, for he cannot 'ſcape,</l>
                     <l>Leſt wildneſs conquering my ſafer ſenſe</l>
                     <l>Thruſt forth my hand into and act of horror,</l>
                     <l>And leave you breathleſs here. Will you diſcloſe?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
                     <l>What <hi>French Neronian</hi> Spirit have we here?</l>
                     <l>Inſolent boy wilt thou turn Parracide?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clov.</speaker>
                     <l>The Juſtice of my cauſe would well excuſe me,</l>
                     <l>Iſ I ſhould execute: ſpeak Murthereſs,</l>
                     <l>Where have you mew'd your Monſter?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>2.</speaker>
                     <l>Here lies the Monſter; O rare Monſter; two beards, I'le pul</l>
                     <l>On this too that's certain, two heads O delicate dainty Monſter.</l>
                     <pb n="41" facs="tcp:57541:23"/>
                     <l> What a brave Monſter ſhall I be, the Conſtable himſelf.</l>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>he in the Habit of</hi> Child. <hi>of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers to ſteal by.</hi>
                     </stage>
                     <l>Cannot make a better Monſter, I will ſteal by theſe, get</l>
                     <l>Me home, ſell theſe gay cloaths, buy half a dram of Juſtice</l>
                     <l>And be a Monſter of the Peace immediately.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clov.</speaker>
                     <l>Will you confeſs, or—drop oh mine eye-balls out</l>
                     <l>And thou my ſollid fleſh diſſolve to earth.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lam.</speaker>
                     <p>How fares it with your Grace? Great Monſieur ſpeak.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clov.</speaker>
                     <l>Look there <hi>Lamot</hi> ſeeſt thou that horrid ſhape,</l>
                     <l>Which I unjuſtly did but now uſurp;</l>
                     <l>Looks it not like the King, <hi>Lamot</hi> what ſay'ſt thou?</l>
                     <l>Shall I go kneel to't, call it honour'd Father,</l>
                     <l>And beg a pardon for my treſpaſs done?</l>
                     <l>It would depart, but I will call it back:</l>
                     <l>Stay thou bleſt ſpirit, Royal father, thru,</l>
                     <l>Behold thy ſon, thy <hi>Clovis</hi> on his knees,</l>
                     <l>O pardon gentle ſpirit pardon me.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>2.</speaker>
                     <l>That's my good Boy, riſe, but d'ye hear ſirrah,</l>
                     <l>Put no more tricks nor gulls upon me; my ſon,</l>
                     <l>I have but one and he's three quarters rogue by this time;</l>
                     <l>He's e'n as like thee as over he can peep,</l>
                     <l>Bleſs my Boy, I like him n're the better for't</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clov.</speaker>
                     <l>What ſtrange illuſion's this? what art thou, ſpeak,</l>
                     <l>Or I will nail thee dead againſt the wall.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>2.</speaker>
                     <l>Juſt ſuch another Rogue have I to my ſon as this;</l>
                     <l>He has his very words too, thou art mine own,</l>
                     <l>I wonder where I got thee, canſt not thou remember?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lam.</speaker>
                     <l>Villain?</l>
                     <l>How cam'ſt thou by that babit? who ar't, ſpeak?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>2.</speaker>
                     <l>Is it the Monſieur? I have made a brave hand on't then;</l>
                     <l>Lord, Lord, ſee how good cloaths makes us forget our ſelves:</l>
                     <l>My name is <hi>Potſhot,</hi> my trade a Cobler,</l>
                     <l>One of the Conſtables Watch in extraordinary;</l>
                     <l>And if you will believe me Mr. Monſieur,</l>
                     <l>It went againſt my ſtomach very much,</l>
                     <l>That you ſhould daro preſume to call me father,</l>
                     <l>Oh, oh, oh, oh!</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Colv.</speaker>
                     <p>Tell me how thou cam'ſt by thoſe cloaths? I'le pardon thee.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>2.</speaker>
                     <l>Truly I came lawfully by them, for I ſtole them,</l>
                     <l>The devil and I fought 15 hours for them,</l>
                     <l>He broke my head a dozen times at leaſt;</l>
                     <l>At l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ſt I maul'd the raſcal, and he lies there.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lam.</speaker>
                     <l>Behold my Lord, the Woodcock's in the gin,</l>
                     <l>Here lies the great <hi>Landrey.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
                     <p>O horrid ſin.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <pb n="42" facs="tcp:57541:24"/>
                     <speaker>Clov.</speaker>
                     <l>This habit might have ruin'd all, <hi>Lamot,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>But Goblin now you're caught; what is he dead?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lam.</speaker>
                     <p>Scarce hurt my Lord; how is it Sir, look up?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>2.</speaker>
                     <p>Is not the devil dead?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clov.</speaker>
                     <p>Hold hold, you have done well.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>2.</speaker>
                     <p>Then whiſtle Jack-a-dandy.</p>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>Enter</hi> Eunuch <hi>haſtily.</hi>
                     </stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
                     <p>Where is the Queen?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
                     <p>Here Eunuch as thou ſeeſt in miſery.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
                     <p>On my heart, how came they hither? <hi>Lamot</hi> too?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
                     <p>All that I know is that we are betray'd.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
                     <p>I'le ſet them packing fear't nor; My good Lord</p>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>whiſpers with</hi> Clovis.</stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>2.</speaker>
                     <l>D'ye hear friend <hi>Lucifer,</hi> what Cat's your father?</l>
                     <l>How many lives have you got, ha diabolo?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clov.</speaker>
                     <p>Thou art a faithfull ſervant.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
                     <p>Sir, the Rebells.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clov.</speaker>
                     <l>Give them a nobler title, by my life</l>
                     <l>I do applaud their courage, come they on?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
                     <p>Yes, and <hi>Br<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ſſac</hi> is made their General.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clov.</speaker>
                     <l>A hopefull Youth fraught with nobility,</l>
                     <l>And all the gracefull qualities that write.</l>
                     <l>Man truly honourable, mine injuries.</l>
                     <l>Have ſtirr'd him up to this.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
                     <p>His father's dead.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clov.</speaker>
                     <l>Truſt me I'me ſorry for't, grief has broke his heart.</l>
                     <l>And mine <hi>Caſtrato,</hi> too: can'ſt thou imagine</l>
                     <l>Who was the authors of our father's death?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
                     <l>Am I betray'd, then, lend mo confidence,</l>
                     <l>I'me ſure I cannot bluſh; Royal Sir, whom?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clov.</speaker>
                     <l>Our Mother and <hi>Landrey,</hi> and this <hi>Lamot.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>They meant ſhould bear the blame: this was <hi>Strephon.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
                     <p>It's wondrous ſtrange, Would I were fairly off.</p>
                     <stage>aſide.</stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clov.</speaker>
                     <p>But what news with <hi>Aphelia,</hi> and her Bridegroom?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
                     <l>As you could wiſh, he's full of ielouſy,</l>
                     <l>No <hi>Frenchman</hi> e're was more <hi>Italian,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>I've wrought him bravely on, your Phyſick works;</l>
                     <l>Hither I've brought <hi>Aphelia</hi> too: tomorrow</l>
                     <l>You ſhall hear further; ſport I'le warrant you.</l>
                     <l>What will you do with theſe?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clov.</speaker>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Caſtrato,</hi> thus:</l>
                     <l>Nature forbids me ſpill my Mothers bloud,</l>
                     <l>And <hi>Landrey</hi> is unfi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> for my revenge,</l>
                     <l>For I muſt ſtudy torments for the ſlave,</l>
                     <l>Therefore I give them upto your tuition</l>
                     <l>Untill we ſhall return victorious.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <pb n="43" facs="tcp:57541:24"/>
                     <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
                     <p>Obſerve you that, there is ſome comfort yet.</p>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>aſide to</hi> Lan</stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clov.</speaker>
                     <l>Then we'le determine of them; if we fall</l>
                     <l>Let <hi>Clotaire</hi> point them out a funeral;</l>
                     <l>Reward this fellow largely with our Purſe,</l>
                     <l>His merits are 2000 Crowns, perform it.</l>
                     <stage>gives him a purſe.</stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>2.</speaker>
                     <l>The Lord preſerve my Son, I mean the Monſieur,</l>
                     <l>I truly did I, I was overjoy'd,</l>
                     <l>And knew not what I ſaid, no truly Son.</l>
                     <l>If I can keep all this wealth without running mad,</l>
                     <l>Then <hi>Potſhot</hi> may become an Alderman:</l>
                     <l>Drink I adore thee, drink good fellows all,</l>
                     <l>Sometimes we riſe by drink, but oftner fall.</l>
                     <l>O me, what a rare thing it is to be a Monſter.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Exit.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clov.</speaker>
                     <l>A moral drunkard. Go away with them,</l>
                     <l>And on your life let them not ſtir from hence.</l>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>Exit</hi> Eu. Qu. <hi>and</hi> Lan.</stage>
                     <l>Now my revenge grows to maturity,</l>
                     <l>We'le to <hi>Dumaine, Lamot,</hi> and joyn with him:</l>
                     <l>Now <hi>France,</hi> thou ly'ſt a bleeding, thou ſhalt prove</l>
                     <l>What 'tis to croſs the Monſieur in his Love.</l>
                     <stage>Exeunt omnes</stage>
                  </sp>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="act">
               <head>ACT <hi>V.</hi>
               </head>
               <div n="1" type="scene">
                  <head>SCENE <hi>I.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Drum. Enter</hi> Charles Briſſac, Dumaine, Burbon, Lanone, Martel.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Dum.</speaker>
                     <p>For certain then the Princes are at odds.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Briſ</speaker>
                     <p>Yes, and grounds the marriage of my Siſter.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Burb.</speaker>
                     <p>The ulcerous State is ripe, and we muſt launce it.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Briſ.</speaker>
                     <l>The King does whore my Siſter; ſhe's not his,</l>
                     <l>But true and Lawfully the Monſieurs Wife.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Dum.</speaker>
                     <p>Did not one <hi>Strephon</hi> wait upon the Prince?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Briſ.</speaker>
                     <p>Yes, ſuch there was, but little noids'd at Court.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Dum.</speaker>
                     <p>That was <hi>Lamot</hi> our faſt and noble friend.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Burb.</speaker>
                     <p>I wonder that we hear not from him yet.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lanoue.</speaker>
                     <p>There's ſome deſign on foot that hinders him.</p>
                     <stage>a ſhout within.</stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Dum.</speaker>
                     <p>What means this noiſe? <hi>Martel</hi> ſtep forth and ſee.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Briſ.</speaker>
                     <l>The Monſieur! O death we are ſurpiz'd,</l>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>again, crying the</hi> Monſ. <hi>the</hi> Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieur, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                     </stage>
                     <l>Suddenly ſnar'd, let each man to his charge,</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Burb.</speaker>
                     <p>Heark ſtill the noiſe encreaſeth.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lanoue.</speaker>
                     <l>By the ſound</l>
                     <stage>again.</stage>
                     <pb n="44" facs="tcp:57541:25"/>
                     <l> This is a ſhout of joy, and not of dread.</l>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>Enter</hi> Martel, La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mot, <hi>and</hi> Monſieur.</stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Briſ.</speaker>
                     <p>What news <hi>Martel?</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mart.</speaker>
                     <p>You may inform your ſelf.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mon.</speaker>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Briſſac, Dumaine, Burbon,</hi> and the reſt,</l>
                     <l>Think not I come a Traytor to your Camp,</l>
                     <l>I cannot gild my ſpeech with eloquence,</l>
                     <l>If this will ſerve you, ſo; I am a friend.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Briſ.</speaker>
                     <l>The Monſieur welcome, and his worth will grace</l>
                     <l>The dignity of this days work in hand.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mon.</speaker>
                     <l>My almoſt Brother once, ſuffice, I thank you</l>
                     <l>And fairly greet this brave aſſembly,</l>
                     <l>Whoſe ſouls do look for ſtirring oppoſits,</l>
                     <l>When your reſiſtance I fear will be ſlender.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Briſ.</speaker>
                     <l>If we obtain a glorious victory,</l>
                     <l>Without a crimſon tincture of the Field</l>
                     <l>it will be better: therefore I think it ſit</l>
                     <l>We ſet upon them e're they be prepar'd,</l>
                     <l>Twill ſave much bloud on both ſides.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mon.</speaker>
                     <l>Be it ſo,</l>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>again the</hi> Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiear <hi>within.</hi>
                     </stage>
                     <l>Let us reform the Land, not overthrow.</l>
                     <l>We will about it ſtreight, lead on before.</l>
                     <stage>Exeunt omnes.</stage>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="scene">
                  <head>SCENE <hi>II.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Eunuch ſolus. <hi>He draws a Curtain where</hi> Landrey <hi>ſits bound at one end of the Table, and the</hi> Queen <hi>at the other.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
                     <l>Here ſits our Beldam, dieted for venery:</l>
                     <l>And by her, her <hi>Landrey,</hi> not ſurfeited;</l>
                     <l>Her Ladyſhip's allow'd a mouldy cruſt,</l>
                     <l>He ſtinking water to piece out his life;</l>
                     <l>Between them both they banque<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> like one Slave</l>
                     <l>Condemned perpetually to the Burdello.</l>
                     <l>They think I know not that they thus are uſed,</l>
                     <l>When it is only I that uſe them this.</l>
                     <l>How wickedly they look, on I could laugh,</l>
                     <l>To hear them rail at other's miſery.</l>
                     <l>He curſes her, and ſhe ſooth curſes him,</l>
                     <l>And both each other damn for their offences.</l>
                     <l>Learn ye that pamper up your fleſh to Luſt,</l>
                     <l>The Eunuch in his wickedneſs is Juſt.</l>
                     <pb n="45" facs="tcp:57541:25"/>
                     <l> They ſleep too long, and take too much of eaſe</l>
                     <l>I muſt awake ye, play and play aloud.</l>
                     <stage>Hoboys within.</stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
                     <l>A Miſchief take the keeper, hardned dogg</l>
                     <l>Whom no diſtreſs can melt or molify,</l>
                     <l>The cruel King does not deny us ſleep.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
                     <l>Moſt gentle Queen,</l>
                     <l>I am not guilty of theſe harſh voiced words:</l>
                     <l>Your wilder ſenſe hurles at me; you miſtake.</l>
                     <l>I am your Eunuch one that weeps for you.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
                     <l>Oh <hi>Caſtrato,</hi> waſt not thoſe tear, in vain,</l>
                     <l>Come hither and I'le catch thoſe falling drops</l>
                     <l>Which prodigally overflow their banks,</l>
                     <l>There's nectar in thine eyes, oh let me drink it.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
                     <p>Tho' I be tortur'd for't, I'le relieve ye.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Exit.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
                     <p>It has quencht half my thirſt to find ſome pitty,</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lan.</speaker>
                     <l>One bit of bread tho it were gray with age,</l>
                     <l>Hoary and cruſted with a Second bark,</l>
                     <l>Would ſeem a Banquet to my empty Gorge.</l>
                     <l>Oh, I am worn to nothing with this want,</l>
                     <l>Such emptineſs has hunger made of me</l>
                     <l>That you may draw me on another man.</l>
                     <l>Some bread, ſome bread.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Eunuch <hi>with Wine and Meat, he Cong<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>es to the Quem with great Ceremony.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
                     <l>Oh thou art welcome, quick dear Eunuch quick;</l>
                     <l>Away with form and ceremonious duty:</l>
                     <l>Reſpect in this is too reſpectleſs.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
                     <l>Oh give me leave, I will begin a health,</l>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>e ſips.</hi>
                     </stage>
                     <l>'Tis very good, exceeding pleaſant wine.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
                     <p>Doſt thou deride my ſufferance?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
                     <p>No not I.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
                     <p>Give me the drink then, I'm all flame and fire.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
                     <l>Say you ſo, ſay you ſo, then you muſt pardon;</l>
                     <l>I love your ſafety, and its dangerous</l>
                     <l>To drink while you are hot, pray cool and tarry.</l>
                     <l>In the mean time I will begin to you.</l>
                     <l>How tart and pleaſant this is to the pallat,</l>
                     <l>A Sweeter Pheaſant Chriſtendom affords not.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Land.</speaker>
                     <p>I thank thee Eunuch, protheo give it me.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
                     <l>You'l let me taſt it for you, will you not?</l>
                     <l>Are you ſo haſty: ſtill you are too haſty,</l>
                     <l>Gentle ſir is will digeſt the better.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <pb n="46" facs="tcp:57541:26"/>
                     <speaker>Land.</speaker>
                     <p>More, more, that's excellent.</p>
                     <stage>he unlooſeth his arms a little that he might feed himſelf.</stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
                     <p>Madam here's for you now.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
                     <p>May heaven reward thee for't, oh it is rare.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
                     <p>How do you like your banquet great <hi>Landrey?</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Land.</speaker>
                     <p>Beyond compare.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
                     <p>And you your drink.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
                     <p>The Gods taſt not the like.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
                     <p>Ha, ha, ha, ye have both eat and drunk abominable poiſon,</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
                     <p>Ha?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Land.</speaker>
                     <p>How?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
                     <l>'Tis true I tell you oracle,</l>
                     <l>There's not an hour's life between ye both,</l>
                     <l>The poyſon's ſure, I did prepare it for you;</l>
                     <l>And have my ſelf taken an Antidote.</l>
                     <l>What ſay you to th'other bout now with <hi>Landrey?</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>I can procure another meeting for you,</l>
                     <l>Indeed I can; think you not whoredom ſweet</l>
                     <l>Now you're a dying? is not your ſoul at eaſe?</l>
                     <l>The murther of your Husband's but a toy,</l>
                     <l>A f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>a-biting, alack you feel it not.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
                     <p>Oh Villain, Villain, Villain.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Land.</speaker>
                     <p>Inhumance ſlave, trecherous raſcal.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
                     <l>Goods bobes, are you at Liberty?</l>
                     <stage>Land. <hi>goes from his Chair.</hi>
                     </stage>
                     <l>How got you looſe? a knife too, hoyty toyty.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Land.</speaker>
                     <l>Faintneſs for want of food, I fear will trap me,</l>
                     <l>Yo'r very nimble Raſcal;</l>
                     <stage>Land. <hi>falls following the</hi> Eu. <hi>at a ſhort turn, &amp; being down, the</hi> Eu. <hi>gets upon him &amp; diſarms him.</hi>
                     </stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
                     <l>Oh Lord ſir, you know the cauſe,</l>
                     <l>I'm lighter by a ſtone or two then then you,</l>
                     <l>Yet I am weight enough to keep you down;</l>
                     <l>Stir and thou dy'ſt, now ſir what fay you to me?</l>
                     <l>How do you like your Princeſs? is ſhe gameſome?</l>
                     <l>Did ſhe apply her ſelf like an apt whore</l>
                     <l>Unto your looſe embraces?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
                     <p>Dog, let him riſe.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
                     <l>Pardon me great Madam I beſeech you.</l>
                     <l>Under your Graces favour be it ſpoken,</l>
                     <l>He is our cuſhion and I'le ſit on him;</l>
                     <l>I do not altogether weigh a man.</l>
                     <l>As I live dead, preſt to death without Stones;</l>
                     <l>Stark dead; a very ſtrong-hearted Monſieur,</l>
                     <l>What ſay you to his Statue now in Ginger-bread?</l>
                     <l>It were a Monument too good for <hi>Landrey.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>But ſit thee there again: Once more to you,</l>
                     <stage>ſets him in the Chair again,</stage>
                     <l>Who, if your Poyſon do not work too faſt,</l>
                     <pb n="47" facs="tcp:57541:26"/>
                     <l> Shall ſee more ſights like theſe before you dye,</l>
                     <l>Your Organ-pipe's already out of tune,</l>
                     <l>I'le leave ye a peeping-hole, thro' which you ſhall</l>
                     <stage>leaves the Cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain half open.</stage>
                     <l>See ſights ſhall kill thee faſter then thy poyſon.</l>
                     <l>I am prepared now for <hi>Aphelia's</hi> death,</l>
                     <l>All things are ready, and behold the King;</l>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>Enter</hi> Clot. <hi>ſadly.</hi>
                     </stage>
                     <l>Now for my part.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clot.</speaker>
                     <l>I am too pityfull, a wat'ry flux</l>
                     <l>Which ſoft and tender-hearted men call tears</l>
                     <l>Stand on mine eyes, and does expreſs a nature</l>
                     <l>Too like my barer, it is now with me</l>
                     <l>Full Tide in ſorrow: my <hi>Cint<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ia</hi> governs ſtrongly;</l>
                     <l>What do the wiſe,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Caſtrato,</hi> call this moiſture, which preſumes</l>
                     <l>To mediate betwixt my wrath and me?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
                     <l>Expreſſions of a weak and ſilly nature,</l>
                     <l>Paſſions of fools and women; are you a man</l>
                     <l>And bear ſo tame a ſoul, ſuch a ſmock-ſpirit?</l>
                     <l>The Diſtaff owns more ſpleen, more noble anger:</l>
                     <l>Pray let her live untill the Pages write,</l>
                     <l>And hopping <hi>Ballatire's</hi> voice Rhimes upon you;</l>
                     <l>This will ſound bravely, will it not?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clot.</speaker>
                     <p>Bring her in.</p>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>Enter two lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding</hi> Aph. <hi>in her pertticoat as to be tortur'd.</hi>
                     </stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Aph.</speaker>
                     <l>Uſe not ſuch violence good Gentlemen</l>
                     <l>I'le walk a Lamb to ſlaughter, not repine</l>
                     <l>At any torments ye ſhall put me to;</l>
                     <l>Only be modeſt; commend me to my Lord,</l>
                     <l>I doubt I never ſhall behold him more;</l>
                     <l>For by the Calculation of your looks</l>
                     <l>I have not long to live.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clot.</speaker>
                     <l>Confeſs and turn thy fate, give me to know</l>
                     <l>With what foul Monſter thou haſt wrong'd thy ſoul,</l>
                     <l>Seam-rent that holy weed, Virginity:</l>
                     <l>And eaſe me of a load that bears more weight</l>
                     <l>Then what my youthfull ſins have heap'd upon me.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Aph.</speaker>
                     <p>If ever.—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clot.</speaker>
                     <l>No more of that, it tends to madneſs:</l>
                     <l>I'le force it from thee, bring forth the tortures there,</l>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>a pan of co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ls and ſearing-Irons.</hi>
                     </stage>
                     <l>I'le try if in theſe fiery inſtruments</l>
                     <l>There lies a tongue which better can perſuade</l>
                     <l>Confeſſion from thee, theſe red hot, apply'd</l>
                     <l>Unto thy breaſts, ſhall there extract</l>
                     <l>All future hope to ſuckle lawleſs Iſſue;</l>
                     <l>The poyſonous ſprings which from theſe hills ariſe</l>
                     <pb n="48" facs="tcp:57541:27"/>
                     <l> Shall have their fountain head damn'd up by theſe.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Aph.</speaker>
                     <l>I've heard you ſweat that you were poor in words,</l>
                     <l>And knew not to expreſs the happineſs</l>
                     <l>Which you conceiv'd was habitable here:</l>
                     <l>How much my Lord is alter'd from himſelf!</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clot.</speaker>
                     <l>'Tis thou art alter'd: True, <hi>Aphelia,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>That whil'ſt thy purer thoughts did awe thy will</l>
                     <l>I lov'd like an Idolater; I was poſſeſt</l>
                     <l>That theſe two twins, theſe globes of fleſh, contain'd</l>
                     <l>All that was happy both in earth and heaven;</l>
                     <l>In this I could deſcry the milky way,</l>
                     <l>The Maiden Zone that girds the waſte of heaven;</l>
                     <l>In this the ſeat of Paradiſe, and how</l>
                     <l>The wanton rivolets play'd about the Iſle</l>
                     <l>Which puzzles Geography: All this I could</l>
                     <l>In thee my ſometime chaſt <hi>Aphelia</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Find and rejoyce in, but thou art now</l>
                     <l>An undreſt Wilderneſs, wherein I walk,</l>
                     <l>Loſing my ſelf'mongſt multitudes of beaſts</l>
                     <l>And ſalvage actions: come diſpatch.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Aph.</speaker>
                     <p>Sir—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clot.</speaker>
                     <p>I'le hear no more.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Aph.</speaker>
                     <l>Heaven will then,</l>
                     <l>And tho' it be an ear far diſtant hence,</l>
                     <l>Both hear and pity me: Oh my lov'd Lord,</l>
                     <l>Should but a dream work on my fancy</l>
                     <l>That you were thus to ſuffer as I am,</l>
                     <l>It would conſpire to kill me with more ſpeed</l>
                     <l>Then theſe your threatning Miniſters, alas!</l>
                     <l>I'do force a gentler nature in the Steel,</l>
                     <l>And with my rainy eyes weep out the heat,</l>
                     <l>Which as it dyes ſhould hiſs it ſelf to ſcorn,</l>
                     <l>For offering to contain but ſire to hurt you;</l>
                     <l>And will you then, a bold ſpectator ſtand,</l>
                     <l>Smiling at what I ſuffer? Shed but one tear,</l>
                     <l>Or counterfeit a ſorrow for my ſake,</l>
                     <l>A little ſeeming woe, and I ſhall dye,</l>
                     <l>Sick of your kindneſs, not your cruelty.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clot.</speaker>
                     <l>Oh my ſoft temper, her ſweet harmony</l>
                     <l>Will melt me into fool.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
                     <l>Oh this is brave,</l>
                     <l>A whining Cuckold.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clot.</speaker>
                     <l>Whore, will you confeſs?</l>
                     <l>Speak or I'le break thy heart.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <pb n="49" facs="tcp:57541:27"/>
                     <speaker>Aph.</speaker>
                     <p>My gentle Lord.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clot.</speaker>
                     <l>Ungentle whore thou lyeſt, I am not gentle,</l>
                     <l>Thou canſt not catch me more with oyly ſounds,</l>
                     <l>Speak ſwiftly to my words, whoſe whore art thou?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Aph.</speaker>
                     <l>My gracious Prince, I dare not call you husband,</l>
                     <l>Your actions do forbid, which write me ſlave</l>
                     <l>And not your equal: if to be your wife</l>
                     <l>Has plucked this miſery upon my head,</l>
                     <l>Or cauſed in you this phrenſie, put me off;</l>
                     <l>I will indure it patiently; but if e're—</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clot.</speaker>
                     <p>The old tune this, come come the Irons there.</p>
                     <stage>they ſear one of her breſts.</stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Aph.</speaker>
                     <l>Oh, oh, oh, cruel my Lord, unmanly,</l>
                     <l>I'le not blaſpheme, no nor think ill of Heaven;</l>
                     <l>Altho' my injuries would half perſuade,</l>
                     <l>Gods are not, or are deaf to Innocents.</l>
                     <stage>Drum. Enter a Meſſenger haſtily.</stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>1. <hi>Meſ.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <l>Arm, arm my Lord, the Caſtle's wall'd about</l>
                     <l>With living Clay, three times ten thouſand men.</l>
                     <l>Approved Warriors, ſouls of Blood afire,</l>
                     <l>That only know to do, and not to ſuffer,</l>
                     <l>Make head againſt you; believe me ſir,</l>
                     <l>A braver troop, and ſpirits more reſolved,</l>
                     <l>Life never put in action.</l>
                     <stage>Enter another Meſſenger.</stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>2 <hi>Meſ.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>Fly, fly my Lord.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clot.</speaker>
                     <p>Villain it is no Language for a Prince.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>2 <hi>Meſ.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <l>Then ſtand upon your Guard, yet that's as bad,</l>
                     <stage>Drum.</stage>
                     <l>The Caſtle-walls are made of walking Steel,</l>
                     <l>And you but tempt your death in your eſcape</l>
                     <l>If you ſtay here provok't.</l>
                     <l>The Monſieur like the god of war beſtrides</l>
                     <l>A bounding Courſer, who is therefore proud</l>
                     <l>To be ſo backed as knowing whom ſhe bears.</l>
                     <l>So Centaur-like he's anchored to his ſeat</l>
                     <l>As if he had twin'd with the proud Beaſt he rides on,</l>
                     <l>And were incorporate with the Steed that bears him;</l>
                     <l>He grows unto his Saddle all one piece</l>
                     <l>And that unto his Horſe, who thus unmov'd</l>
                     <l>Sits like a <hi>Perſeus</hi> on his <hi>Pegaſſus</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Stable and fleet.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clot.</speaker>
                     <l>Is he joyn'd with them too?</l>
                     <l>Then doomſday is at hand, I ſee my ruine,</l>
                     <l>Go to the Caſtle-walls, and Summon them</l>
                     <l>To render an account of their intents,</l>
                     <pb n="50" facs="tcp:57541:28"/>
                     <l> Away I ſay be gone: Cone hither Eunuch,</l>
                     <l>Look here's a Piſlol, in whoſe womb lies doath,</l>
                     <l>A heavy leaden ſheep.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
                     <l>Would you I ſhould</l>
                     <l>Try the concluſion here? make her confeſs</l>
                     <l>By other inſtruments her horrid guilt?</l>
                     <l>In this there's too much mercy.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clot.</speaker>
                     <l>Her me ſpeak,</l>
                     <l>I'le trouble her no further, let her ſin</l>
                     <l>Be puniſht from above, I'le wait heavens leiſure:</l>
                     <l>Here Eunuch take thou this, it was prepar'd</l>
                     <l>For the adulterate <hi>Landrey;</hi> here receive it,</l>
                     <l>And if thou loveſt me, uſe it upon me;</l>
                     <l>Come ſhoo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> me thro', I know I ſhall be ſlain,</l>
                     <l>If not by thee, yet by the enemy;</l>
                     <l>And therefore to prevent the bitter ſcorn</l>
                     <l>Of the inſulting foe, which is a death</l>
                     <l>So full of horror to the conquered;</l>
                     <l>No tyranny is like it, uſe this handfull,</l>
                     <l>The wholſomeſt weed that nature can produce</l>
                     <l>In the large ſtore-houſe of her providence</l>
                     <l>Can ſhew no ſimple like it, for this cures</l>
                     <l>At once the ſickneſs of the mind and body.</l>
                     <l>Thou ſhalt; I know thou wil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>, I prethee take't,</l>
                     <l>It is not murder (tender hearted fool)</l>
                     <l>That thou committeſt, rather a ſacrifice,</l>
                     <l>For which heaven will reward thee.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
                     <l>I ne're was liker to expreſs my ſelf</l>
                     <l>Then at this minute; do not betray me tears;</l>
                     <l>The Eunuchs nature muſt be harſh and cruel;</l>
                     <l>Tho' I do undertake this deed,</l>
                     <l>Bear witneſs heaven it is againſt my will.</l>
                     <stage>takes the Piſtol.</stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Aph.</speaker>
                     <p>O ſpare him Eunuch, ſpare, ſave my Lord.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
                     <l>Peace fooliſh woman, 'tis thou killeſt thy Lord.</l>
                     <l>Were't not for thee he might live long and happy;</l>
                     <l>Pray let me kiſs your hand, and take my leave</l>
                     <l>Of my beſt, beſt Maſter.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clot.</speaker>
                     <p>Do't and be ſudden then—ha, what means this?</p>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>he whips away</hi> Clotairs <hi>Sword.</hi>
                     </stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
                     <l>Marry Sir this it means,</l>
                     <l>That if this fail this ſhall perform the deed,</l>
                     <l>Think not but I will kill you, do not fear,</l>
                     <l>I am the excelent'ſt alive at theſe toys,</l>
                     <pb n="51" facs="tcp:57541:28"/>
                     <l> Look here my couſened fool I do not bungle.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clot.</speaker>
                     <p>Are theſe dead then?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
                     <l>As ſure as you live, pray ask them elſe,</l>
                     <l>Unleſs this <hi>Eves</hi> fleſh, too intenſe in heat,</l>
                     <l>Be lingring ſtill behind: ſhe's ſcarcely dead,</l>
                     <l>But in her dying cars I'le howl this noiſe:</l>
                     <l>Look Queen, here's the top-branch of all thy family,</l>
                     <l>Mark but how kindly for thy ſake I'le uſe him.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clot.</speaker>
                     <l>Then I perceive I have been much abus'd,</l>
                     <l>So has my deareſt Lady, oh, my heart.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
                     <p>Oh do you ſo? do you ſo?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
                     <p>Oh oh oh!</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
                     <p>There broke a Strumpets heart.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clot.</speaker>
                     <l>How fain would I preſerve my ſelf from death</l>
                     <l>Since my <hi>Aphelia's</hi> chaſt, to think her falſe,</l>
                     <l>Not that I fear'd the ſoe, made me deſpair</l>
                     <l>Of furture comfort: Eunuch ſpare my life,</l>
                     <l>I will forgive thee, and reward thee too:</l>
                     <l>Remember who it is that ſues to thee.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
                     <l>In that remembrance I have loſt my ſelf:</l>
                     <l>I cannot ſtrike him, my relenting heart</l>
                     <l>Erns on his Princely perſon; take your Sword,</l>
                     <l>But on condition <hi>Clotaire;</hi> thou ſhalt ſwear</l>
                     <l>By thy deſcen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>, thy Princely Parentage,</l>
                     <l>By the wrong'd ſouls of all thoſe Innocents,</l>
                     <l>By thy Luſt ſacrific<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>d, by <hi>Aphelia</hi>'s ſelf,</l>
                     <l>Or any thing the ſoul ſhall hold more dear,</l>
                     <l>Upon receipt to guide the fat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>l point</l>
                     <l>Directly to my heart: My time is ſhort,</l>
                     <stage>a Drum beats within.</stage>
                     <l>Quickly diſpatch, reſolve to do or dye,</l>
                     <l>And what ſhall grieve thee more then all the reſt,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Aphelia</hi> ſhall bear thee company.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clot.</speaker>
                     <p>To ſave her life I'le undertake this deed.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
                     <l>I'le teach thee to the ſpeedy in the fact:</l>
                     <l>Remember how thy noble Father dy'd,</l>
                     <l>Into thy boſom caſt thine in ward eyes,</l>
                     <l>And view what ſorrows I have heaped on thee;</l>
                     <l>Behold thy Mother murthered by this hand,</l>
                     <l>Look on this Innocent, and let her wrongs</l>
                     <l>Prompt thy ſlow hand to this moſt timely ſlaughter;</l>
                     <l>I cannot brook delay.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clot.</speaker>
                     <l>Take thy reward.</l>
                     <pb n="52" facs="tcp:57541:29"/>
                     <l> A Heathen and a Traytor dye with thee.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
                     <l>A Chriſtian Heathen <hi>Clotaire</hi> if thou wilt,</l>
                     <l>Made ſo by thee, read that and break thy heart.</l>
                     <stage>ſtings him a note, he ſtands amazed.</stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clovis.</speaker>
                     <l>Force ope the dore,</l>
                     <stage>Enter the Army.</stage>
                     <l>Seize on his Royal Perſon, now <hi>Clotaire</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Thou art the Monſieur's pris'ner, Tyrant ſay</l>
                     <l>Where is <hi>Aphelia</hi> your Adultereſs?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Briſ.</speaker>
                     <p>O my dear Sifter.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clov.</speaker>
                     <p>O moſt horrid ſight; my mother &amp; <hi>Landr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>y</hi> both murthered.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Dum.</speaker>
                     <l>Here lies that Villain Eunuch: Hell hound up:</l>
                     <l>Wnoſe hauds have ſlain thy Miſtreſs?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
                     <l>No<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>e of mine.</l>
                     <l>They'r near ally'd to thee that did this deed,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ilda</hi> and a woman.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Dum.</speaker>
                     <l>Villain thou ly'ſt my ſiſter's gone a weary pilgrimago</l>
                     <l>And for this twice five years (With grief I ſpeak ti)</l>
                     <l>Been wandring none knows where.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clot.</speaker>
                     <l>What am I?</l>
                     <l>What ſtrange and uncouth thing?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
                     <l>A Raviſher;</l>
                     <l>Aud better to inftruct thee in thy ſelf</l>
                     <l>Had not <hi>Corotilda</hi> been inceſtuous.</l>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>the</hi> King <hi>offers to kill himſelf.</hi>
                     </stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>
                        <hi>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>um.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <l>Hold hold your. Royal hand, what will</l>
                     <l>You do?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clot.</speaker>
                     <l>What elſe but follow her? ſhall <hi>Clotaire</hi> live</l>
                     <l>A Capt in to his Brother, ſlaved in ſin,</l>
                     <l>Inthral'd in wedlock, that's inceſtuous?</l>
                     <l>A Raviſher, and Murtherer of his friend,</l>
                     <l>There's no way left to rid me but my Sword</l>
                     <l>Or all theſe ills at once. Oh my <hi>Chrotilda:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>falls upon the</hi> Eir. <hi>weeping.</hi>
                     </stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Dum.</speaker>
                     <p>My Siſter?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clot.</speaker>
                     <l>Ay <hi>Dumain:</hi> no Eunuch ſhe,</l>
                     <l>No Sun-burnt vagabond of <hi>Aetiope</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Tho' entertain'd for ſuch by <hi>Fred<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>gond<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>I ſay here lyes thy raviſht ſiſter, ſlain</l>
                     <l>By me the Raviſher.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Dum.</speaker>
                     <p>Hold, hold my heart.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
                     <l>I forgive thee <hi>Clotaire;</hi> freely forgive thee</l>
                     <l>And let <hi>Aphelia</hi> do the like to me:</l>
                     <l>I bare to her no maliçe; only this,</l>
                     <l>I would not have her to enjoy the man</l>
                     <l>That had ſo near relation unto me.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <pb n="53" facs="tcp:57541:29"/>
                     <speaker>Clov.</speaker>
                     <p>This writes thee perfect <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
                     <l>Lend me thy hand <hi>Clotaire</hi> h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ve I thy hand;</l>
                     <l>I ſhould have kill'd thee King, and had put on</l>
                     <l>A maſculine ſpirit to perform the deed:</l>
                     <l>Alas how frail our reſolutions are,</l>
                     <l>A Woman's weakneſs conquer'd my revenge,</l>
                     <l>I'd Power enough to quit my parents wrongs:</l>
                     <l>And they which ſhould have ſeen me act my part,</l>
                     <l>Would not believe I ſhould ſo ſoon prove Haggard:</l>
                     <l>But there is ſomething dwells upon thy brow</l>
                     <l>that did perſuade me to Humanity:</l>
                     <l>Thou Injureſt me, and yet I ſpar'd thy life,</l>
                     <l>Thou injureſt me, yet I would dye by thee;</l>
                     <l>And like to my loſt ſex, I fall and Periſh.</l>
                     <stage>ſhe dyes,</stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clot.</speaker>
                     <p>Speak for ever, ſpeak <hi>Chrotilda.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Dum.</speaker>
                     <l>Farewell great Heart,</l>
                     <l>My ſiſter's in mine eyes, this brave revenge</l>
                     <l>Should have been mine, and not thine act, <hi>Chrotilda,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Away ſalt Rhume, <hi>Chrotilda</hi> laughs at thee,</l>
                     <l>Her ſpirit was more manly.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Aph.</speaker>
                     <l>I muſt weep too,</l>
                     <l>Her injuries and mine are ſo near kin,</l>
                     <l>That they muſt bare each other Company</l>
                     <l>In tears of blond and death. Brother I faint,</l>
                     <l>And my griev'd heart too long with death oppreſt,</l>
                     <l>Would gladly ſeek a way to find out reſt.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clot.</speaker>
                     <l>Art thou joyn'd with her too, againſt thy ſelf?</l>
                     <l>Will my <hi>Aphelia</hi> leave me?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Aph.</speaker>
                     <l>For ever King,</l>
                     <l>The hand of heaven lyes on me: for I feel</l>
                     <l>My inward and external injuries</l>
                     <l>Wreſtle with life, in which Contention</l>
                     <l>My ſoul is worried by that tyrant death,</l>
                     <l>I muſt forſake thee <hi>Clotaire.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clot.</speaker>
                     <l>Stay a while,</l>
                     <l>It is unkindly done to leave me thus:</l>
                     <l>Oh ſhe is gone, for ever, ever gone,</l>
                     <stage>ſhe dyes.</stage>
                     <l>And I ſtand prating here between them both,</l>
                     <l>The fatal cauſe of death unto them both.</l>
                     <l>Wilt thou not break proud heart, I prethee break,</l>
                     <l>Prove not a Rebell to thy Prince like theſe!</l>
                     <l>It's well there is ſome Loyalty in thee yet,</l>
                     <stage>he falls into a Chair betwixt them both</stage>
                     <l>Thou art commanded by me:</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <pb n="54" facs="tcp:57541:30"/>
                     <speaker>Briſ.</speaker>
                     <p>Gratious Leige.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clot.</speaker>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Charles</hi> I have injur'd thee, and thee <hi>Dumaine,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Can ye forgive me.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Dum.</speaker>
                     <l>Good your grace</l>
                     <l>Call back your ſpirits, think what's to be done.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clot.</speaker>
                     <l>I conſider well; and the great King</l>
                     <l>The quondam Monſieur, ſhall not deny me this:</l>
                     <l>Half of the Honours of the dead <hi>Landrey</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>We do conſer on thee; the other half</l>
                     <l>Be thi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>e <hi>Dumaine, Charles</hi> ſhall be Duke of <hi>France,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Thou of the Pallace Major: this is our will.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Dum.</speaker>
                     <p>Great King you are not ſo near your death.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lam.</speaker>
                     <p>Forfende it heaven.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Monſ.</speaker>
                     <p>Look up thy gracious Brother.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clot.</speaker>
                     <l>I begin to faint,</l>
                     <l>A Darkneſs like to death hangs on mine eyes:</l>
                     <l>Give me thy hand <hi>Briſſac,</hi> and thine <hi>Dumaine.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Good Gentle ſouls, when ye ſhall mention me,</l>
                     <l>And Elder time ſhall rip theſe actions up,</l>
                     <l>Diſſected and anotomized by you,</l>
                     <l>Touch ſparingly this ſtory, do not read</l>
                     <l>T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>o harſh a comment on this loathed deed,</l>
                     <l>Leſt you inforce poſterity to blaſt</l>
                     <l>My name and memory with endleſs curſes:</l>
                     <l>Call me a honourable murtherer:</l>
                     <l>And finiſh there as I do.</l>
                     <stage>he dyes</stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Dum.</speaker>
                     <l>O Noble Prince</l>
                     <l>Whoſe fame was ver<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> eſſence to his ſoul,</l>
                     <l>That gone, the other fled: chuſing to dye</l>
                     <l>Rather then live a Prince <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>nfamy.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Monſ.</speaker>
                     <l>A heavy ſpectacle of grief and wot,</l>
                     <l>Have we beheld ſince our arrival here;</l>
                     <l>Take up the body of the King, and theſe,</l>
                     <l>Which for his ſake on either hand lye ſlain,</l>
                     <l>They ſhall be buried in one monument:</l>
                     <l>And take up theſe: this was a Royal Queen</l>
                     <l>When virtue ſteer'd her thoughts, but we may ſee,</l>
                     <l>When we turn foes to good, to vice a friend,</l>
                     <stage>a dead March &amp; Recorders.</stage>
                     <l>We ſall like theſe, and like theſe, thus we end.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Exeunt Omnes.</stage>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
